<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>David Ralph Lewis</title>
  <subtitle>Poet and writer</subtitle>
  <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/" />
  <updated>2024-06-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name>David Ralph Lewis</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Quick Dice Poetry Exercise</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-06-22-Quick-Dice-Poetry-Exercise/" />
    <updated>2024-06-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-06-22-Quick-Dice-Poetry-Exercise/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I wrote about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/creativity-lessons-from-dnd/&quot;&gt;creativity and &lt;em&gt;Dungeons and Dragons&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, I mentioned I had adapted roll tables to create a random poetry prompt. I thought I&#39;d write up the process in case it&#39;s useful for anyone else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got this idea from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.roleplayingtips.com/gm-books/tiny-prep/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tiny Prep&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is a way to create dungeons by rolling dice. You leave the decisions of creativity up to chance and it helps you start writing without judgement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This exercise is meant to be quick, no more than 5 minutes. You just need two standard dice (d6).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First pick a prompt. Roll a dice and write about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A memory&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What you can currently sense (see, hear, feel, taste)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A random word (generators like &lt;a href=&quot;https://randomwordgenerator.com/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; are useful.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A random photo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open a book at a random page and choose a phrase at random.[^1]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A headline from a magazine or newspaper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can set a timer for five minutes and free write to this prompt to see what comes up, or you can try to restrain it further. Recently I&#39;ve been rolling a second dice to guide the type and form of writing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a haiku&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a tanka&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a cinquain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a sestet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a vivid description, using as much detail as possible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Free write&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could also roll another dice to set the time if you want. Can you write a sestet in a minute? Genuine question as I have no idea!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find this exercise gives me a good starting point for a poem, something I can build on and adapt. Hope it helps you start some poems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[^1]: This is known as bibliomancy&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Always That Chimeric Skyline</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-05-29-Always-That-Chimeric-Skyline/" />
    <updated>2024-05-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-05-29-Always-That-Chimeric-Skyline/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Streets now sliced streaks of&lt;br&gt;
shimmering turquoise, scarlet and&lt;br&gt;
funeral grey blurs, suggestions of&lt;br&gt;
doors, signs and windows barely&lt;br&gt;
registering. How long, running for a&lt;br&gt;
lifetime? No wheezes, no stitches, no&lt;br&gt;
sweat. Pavement treadmills, that&lt;br&gt;
red car ahead suspended in&lt;br&gt;
motion. I need to catch up. Why? No&lt;br&gt;
time for questions. Legs now&lt;br&gt;
pistons, push my hazy memory of a&lt;br&gt;
body forever forward as the city&lt;br&gt;
loops over again towards the&lt;br&gt;
vanishing point, never reached —&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Creativity lessons from Dungeons and Dragons</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-05-24-Creativity-lessons%20from-DnD/" />
    <updated>2024-05-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-05-24-Creativity-lessons%20from-DnD/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the last few years, I&#39;ve been playing &lt;em&gt;Dungeons and Dragons&lt;/em&gt; as a Dungeon Master. This is the person who creates the world and encounters for the players to explore. Every session is fun and I enjoy inventing increasingly strange situations for the party to react to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whilst running the game, I&#39;ve learnt some lessons that are useful for any creative field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Don&#39;t start with a blank page&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When starting to plan an adventure, you might find yourself blocked. It could be set in outer space, a mine, a fantasy town or any other countless situations. This complete open-ended situation may cause writers block. You may have no idea where to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, with Dungeons and Dragons you can use existing materials to start. There&#39;s tons of adventures, a lot of them free, that can give you an initial structure to explore. I used &lt;em&gt;Lost Mines of Phandelver&lt;/em&gt; which is in the starter set when I was first playing. I adapted and changed it as I went along, ending up in a different place but using the framework as a guide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if that feels too daunting, you can start small. There&#39;s whole communities online dedicated to generating ideas for games, from monsters to taverns to towns and characters. One of the best thing that comes out of these communities is roll tables. There&#39;s a list of options, and you roll a dice to pick which one to start with, leaving the decision to chance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say you don&#39;t know what to do in a session. You roll on a couple of tables, get goblins for monsters and a windmill as a location. Now you can get more specific. Why are the goblins in a windmill? Are they looking for something? What issues do they have? By using roll tables, it provides prompts to help you get started. You avoid the shock of the blank page. It&#39;s why I love prompts so much for poetry as well. They set you down a path and start the gears turning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been using a very simple roll table as a warm up for poems, I&#39;ll write about it in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Ideas are cheap&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these roll tables are usually available for free. There&#39;s an implicit agreement in the vast homebrew Dungeons and Dragons community that the ideas are there to be taken.  Each Dungeon Master will use the idea in a different way, depending on the people they are playing with and their world they are making. Every group of players will react to the idea differently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ideas by themselves are not what makes the game. It&#39;s how the individuals use them, what elements they choose to emphasise,  how that idea is developed, how it is described to the players and how the idea is combined with others to make a living fantasy world. The how is much more important than the what.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this is useful in pretty much any creative field as well. You can have the same idea for a poem or painting as another artist, but the way you develop it will be wildly different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Creativity is best when it is a collaboration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One huge mindshift in running a game is you aren&#39;t the sole storyteller. Unlike writing short stories, it&#39;s a collaboration between you and the players. They are not following a series of scenes you have planned, they have freedom to go and do what they want in the world. As such, the game is a collaboration between the Dungeon Master and the players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the best moments in my game have when my players did something completely unexpected, like holding the obviously evil mayor hostage or pushing cult members into a gelatinous cube. I never planned for these moments, but the game allowed for it. In the collaborative space, I am surprised and challenged in the best way, creating a better story than I would have made by myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Above all, Have fun&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote before about how we need &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/art-is-play/&quot;&gt;more play in our artistic practise&lt;/a&gt; . Dungeons and Dragons is not a novel, or a film, it is a game. And games are fun. Ultimately, it helps to not take myself too seriously and to hold my ideas lightly. It&#39;s something I want to take forward more in my other creative work, to have fun with the work and be silly.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Ritual</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-05-14-A-Ritual/" />
    <updated>2024-05-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-05-14-A-Ritual/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been unable to describe the shape&lt;br&gt;
of my body. Birds sing laments, mourning&lt;br&gt;
for our forgotten winter in a language&lt;br&gt;
only they know, nonsense to me. The sky&lt;br&gt;
is a sermon printed on cheap paper,&lt;br&gt;
orange markers bleeding through the page.&lt;br&gt;
My garden whispers like a fading dream&lt;br&gt;
as thoughts transmute to smoke,&lt;br&gt;
wisp and separate and float. Recently&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;too many people have died. This fog cloud&lt;br&gt;
of breath, this speaking in mist feels&lt;br&gt;
like a betrayal. Against whom I am not sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I watch beech leaves sway like incense,&lt;br&gt;
invent new scripts in goose pimples,&lt;br&gt;
inhale the sharp scent of lemon balm,&lt;br&gt;
that has started to grow through patio cracks.&lt;br&gt;
Here is my hand, the pale and blotchy skin,&lt;br&gt;
the small scars from cooking mishaps&lt;br&gt;
the squat thumb. Here, it is reaching&lt;br&gt;
to hold the still warm coffee cup,&lt;br&gt;
vapours of steam like prayers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Listen. The robin and the chiff chaff&lt;br&gt;
are starting to form full sentences.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>&quot;G Man&quot;</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-05-03-G%20man/" />
    <updated>2024-05-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-05-03-G%20man/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When asked to provide an account&lt;br&gt;
he spoke only in pollen drifts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the interrogation room the air&lt;br&gt;
was thick with drifting spores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking this as being unco-operative&lt;br&gt;
the attending agent fetched freedom tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outer leaves were sliced off to start&lt;br&gt;
but vines, thick and choking, grew back&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to fill the holes left behind. He smiled.&lt;br&gt;
Each visible tooth a bud about to open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attempts to dislodge the subject from the chair&lt;br&gt;
were unsuccessful as he had rooted through&lt;br&gt;
the concrete floor, sending fingers deep&lt;br&gt;
below the complex, into the vengeful soil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Insurgent! We cried, Unpatriotic betrayer!&lt;br&gt;
but he just laughed in swallow murmurations&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;before expanding like alliums in May,&lt;br&gt;
growing to grab the walls with bindweed tendrils.&lt;br&gt;
Shots were fired but only blooms exploded.&lt;br&gt;
Still, he grew, shattering the one way glass,&lt;br&gt;
his smile now stretching from wall to wall,&lt;br&gt;
his hair digging into the ceiling tile cracks.&lt;br&gt;
Agents Symonds and Mikowski were lost, bodies&lt;br&gt;
converted to compost. We sealed the bomb  doors&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;cut off section 4A, but even now the metal buckles,&lt;br&gt;
Even now we have teams working around the clock&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ready with secateurs held in shaking hands&lt;br&gt;
watching for that first suggestion of green.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Recording</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-04-22-Recording/" />
    <updated>2024-04-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-04-22-Recording/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2024/recording.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;I found an old tape recorder/ conveyor belt of rhythm/a strange reconstruction/of this improvised night./ I danced/ in the cold darkness&quot; title=&quot;*click* *hisssss*&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erasure poem taken from &lt;em&gt;Tracing the Lines Magazine&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How long until your inlet valve chokes up</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-04-19-How-long-until-your-inlet-valve-chokes-up/" />
    <updated>2024-04-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-04-19-How-long-until-your-inlet-valve-chokes-up/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;with lint and grime? Oil seeps into every&lt;br&gt;
exposed surface, delays the build up of rust,&lt;br&gt;
but decline is inevitable. When did you last&lt;br&gt;
consider your camshaft bearing, your crankshaft&lt;br&gt;
drillings, your line shaft? You forgot to follow&lt;br&gt;
the established maintenance schedule,&lt;br&gt;
didn&#39;t you? Made a checklist then delayed&lt;br&gt;
consulting it. Eventually, your pistons&lt;br&gt;
will stop pumping, a spark plug will fail,&lt;br&gt;
your alternator will burn out or a wire&lt;br&gt;
to your battery will fray. How much grease&lt;br&gt;
lines the walls of your intake manifold?&lt;br&gt;
Is it enough? When did a professional&lt;br&gt;
last give you a look over? Your catalytic&lt;br&gt;
convertor is clogged, you are speaking&lt;br&gt;
in toxic fumes. How long has your engine&lt;br&gt;
management light been flashing on and off?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Days Stack Up</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-04-12-The%20Days%20Stack%20Up/" />
    <updated>2024-04-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-04-12-The%20Days%20Stack%20Up/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently, I was speaking to someone about journaling, and I casually mentioned I&#39;d kept a diary consistently for over ten years. As I said it, it seemed wrong, so I checked the next day. Yup. Over ten years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That seemed crazy to me. My journals cover my whole relationship with my wife, moving to a new city, moving out of the city, various different jobs, my whole history of writing poetry and short stories, the creation of this website, and various adventures, challenges and changes too numerous to list out here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I had to point to any habit that has has the most impact on my life, it would be this one. The act of writing down your thoughts is a special kind of alchemy- it transmutes the vague and unknowable to concrete and actionable. It is a form of meditation where you are able to reflect on the events in your life from an outside perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My journal/ diary has taken many forms over the years. For a while, I wrote everything down in the same book, then split this out into various notebooks by type; to-dos, creative work and a more traditional diary to name a few. I used Linda Barry&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.themarginalian.org/2014/12/02/lynda-barry-syllabus-book/&quot;&gt;observation journal method&lt;/a&gt; for a while. Now days I follow &lt;a href=&quot;https://bulletjournal.com/blogs/faq&quot;&gt;the bullet journal method&lt;/a&gt;, putting all my disparate thoughts and actions in one book, but with a little more structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What has been consistent though, is the act of writing down what has happened and reflecting on it. I don&#39;t tend to write in it every day but usually every two or three. Any longer and the events become distant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When procrastinating, I often watch people sharing their own journals on YouTube, to see how other people organise their thoughts on paper. Often these people espouse the importance of journaling for productivity. While this is one benefit, I would argue it&#39;s not the main one. The point is to observe how you are feeling, what has happened and the world around you from an outside perspective.  It&#39;s about sitting with the blank page, slowly filling it with messy handwriting and emptying your head. In a strange way, this allows you to be more present, as it primes you to observe the world, looking for details to write down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually the blank pages become a month, become a book, become a year, become a decade. The pages and days stack up beside you, become a tower. Eventually you notice patterns in your thinking and your actions. You make changes. You adjust. You re-evaluate. But every time you are brought back to the present moment, staring down the blank page again. Each time you open the journal, you begin again. What have you done? What are you thinking about? What is right in front of you? Breathe. Observe.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Discovering My Allergy to Scallops</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-04-05-Discovering%20My%20Allergy%20to%20Scallops/" />
    <updated>2024-04-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-04-05-Discovering%20My%20Allergy%20to%20Scallops/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&#39;You don&#39;t want to end up like me,&#39;&lt;br&gt;
the man on stage screeches.&lt;br&gt;
Laughter unstoppable now, like&lt;br&gt;
a falling body embracing gravity.&lt;br&gt;
&#39;I&#39;m serious. Why is that funny?&#39;&lt;br&gt;
I feel three hundred people&#39;s heat&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;so I shift outside my self, ceiling&lt;br&gt;
too low, too close, I can&#39;t climb far,&lt;br&gt;
watch myself from above, stumble&lt;br&gt;
past seated and slumped patrons&lt;br&gt;
into the comfort of a dark aisle&lt;br&gt;
&#39;It wasn&#39;t that bad, was it?&#39;&lt;br&gt;
I hear far below, carried upwards&lt;br&gt;
on the whistle of cold air&lt;br&gt;
before heavy auditorium doors&lt;br&gt;
swing open, release me in a rush.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I pull up now, seeking space&lt;br&gt;
my head a dot below as I fly.&lt;br&gt;
Bald patch not as bad as I thought&lt;br&gt;
The world retreats to silence&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a woman speaks in gusts and squalls&lt;br&gt;
pull the ripcord in my head&lt;br&gt;
catch an updraft, higher now,&lt;br&gt;
float in a sea of absence&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a person collapsing below&lt;br&gt;
distant panic and laughter&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Pressure Drop</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-04-01-Pressure-Drop/" />
    <updated>2024-04-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-04-01-Pressure-Drop/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2024/pressure.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: That lonely sky has dimmed./ That bitter cold wind is in us&quot; title=&quot;shiver of not quite summer rattles through me, storm approaching.&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erasure poem taken from &lt;em&gt;Good On Paper&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve  found myself drawn back to erasures recently, because I find them quite meditative. There are some poems drafted but I need to push them over the line. Everything in it&#39;s own time.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Goal</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-03-22-Goal/" />
    <updated>2024-03-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-03-22-Goal/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2024/goal.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: I hope to fall/ into a state/ of deep tenderness&quot; title=&quot;something for us all to aim for&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erasure poem taken from &lt;em&gt;Crack Magazine&lt;/em&gt; editorial&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Vapour Whisper</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-03-12-Vapour-Whisper/" />
    <updated>2024-03-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-03-12-Vapour-Whisper/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2024/vapour.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: I walk towards the sky/ the quiet forming around me/ something indescribable in the ribbons of smoke&quot; title=&quot;the hush of 50,000 ft&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erasure poem taken from &lt;em&gt;Crack Magazine&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>When I took my mattress my duvet and their dreams</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-03-08-When-I-took-my-mattress/" />
    <updated>2024-03-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-03-08-When-I-took-my-mattress/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I said I was keeping them for safety and I almost believed it. I laid down in the middle of the nearest woodland and named it Mine. I rigged canvas between two branches but the wind whistled through my bone marrow. Waking in the night, I started a fire, using their dreams as kindling. I had plenty to spare. Still I did not sleep soundly, So I felled the ancient oaks and built a bed frame from the trunks, raising myself above the cold ground. When this failed, I chopped down every tree I could see, whittled and planed the wood to planks, transformed the land to make myself a shelter, created walls around my bed to define outside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I buried more dreams beneath the floorboards for insulation, allowed them to grow mould spotted and damp. Still I did not sleep soundly. I knew that they would return for their dreams, some day soon. I imagined them all heading over the fields, a large crowd not stopped by frost or rain, for I had taken the dreams of many and named them Mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one came and no one stopped me, so I declared all the surrounding land to be mine, planted thick hedges of briar and thorns and enclosed myself. The rest of their dreams I traded for gold, enough precious metal to hire men with weapons. I made them patrol my borders, watching for trespassers. Still I did not sleep soundly. My duvet felt like steel, my mattress like stone. I sent my militia into neighbouring territories to seek out those who might invade my land, take back their dreams that I hoarded.  As my army conquered and placed a flag that read Mine, my dominion grew, but never by enough. Even as my land reached beyond the horizon I felt a gnawing for what lay beyond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I spent my long nights patrolling my palace, looking out to my silent gardens, thinking I saw the shadows move, the mob come to drag me away and demand what I had stolen from them. I chewed on the last remaining scraps of their dreams, my teeth gluing together, the bitter taste making my eyes water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks as always to Bristol Tonic, whose prompt inspired this poem. I had a lot of fun performing it with improvised harp music.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Gathering</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-02-27-Gathering/" />
    <updated>2024-02-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-02-27-Gathering/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are racing against the dying of the day&lt;br&gt;
over fields flooded with twigs and silence&lt;br&gt;
towards a broiling bruise left by a canula,&lt;br&gt;
our tinny engine whine now a mosquito.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we approach, the cloud swallows the sky&lt;br&gt;
becomes a mountain, navy blue, with illuminated&lt;br&gt;
golden caves. Above our heads it towers,&lt;br&gt;
an impossible island on this empty plain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hold our breaths close, cling to them&lt;br&gt;
like driftwood. As we drive into the dark&lt;br&gt;
rain hammers down onto our metal shell&lt;br&gt;
in a frenzy,  yearning for destruction.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ego Death on the M4</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/ego-death-on-the-m4" />
    <updated>2024-02-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/ego-death-on-the-m4</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am driving home at night&lt;br&gt;
hands gripping the wheel&lt;br&gt;
empty tarmac surrounding me&lt;br&gt;
fertiliser stinging my nostrils&lt;br&gt;
The engine shaking all the space&lt;br&gt;
between my scattered atoms&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;as white lines converge&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;scattered atoms of steel&lt;br&gt;
shake in engine vibrations&lt;br&gt;
fertiliser drifts from nearby fields&lt;br&gt;
the empty tarmac sighs&lt;br&gt;
someone else&#39;s hands grip&lt;br&gt;
a steering wheel as a car&lt;br&gt;
drives on, into darkness.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Three Tips to Declutter Your Life</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/three-tips-to-declutter-your-life" />
    <updated>2024-02-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/three-tips-to-declutter-your-life</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I love performing poetry at open mics and often write poems specifically for performance. This poem is one that is written for the stage, not the page. I read at &lt;a href=&quot;https://solpoetry.org.uk/&quot;&gt;Satellite of Love&lt;/a&gt;&#39;s wonderful open mic recently and &lt;a href=&quot;https://linktr.ee/barryhollow&quot;&gt;Barry Hollow&lt;/a&gt; was kind enough to film it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was actually made from a prompt at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/BristolTonic/&quot;&gt;Bristol Tonic&lt;/a&gt;, which was &amp;quot;Forgotten plastic and flotsam people&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/t09m2PyfJ0I?si=K4hnRvdhjfgHQkGI&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Three Tips to Declutter Your Life&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey everyone, thanks for coming to this seminar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I&#39;m going to talk about how to declutter everything you own in three simple stages. Of course, nothing can be truly owned. Everything is rented or on loan from this world; your car, your house, your body, eventually it will all have to be paid back. Stick around though, Stage three may surprise you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stage 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gather all your plastic containers, your tupperware of various sizes with mismatching lids. Don&#39;t forget your single use wrappers, your Tesco bags and your crisp packets. Whisper all your secrets directly into the plastic, all your fears and regrets, all your feelings and mistakes and misgivings. Now you want to drive to the nearest beach - something that should be significantly easier in the coming years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stage 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just to catch you up in case you didn&#39;t read the study materials, the shore is an argument between ocean and land that the waves are slowly winning. You will want to gather all your detritus, all your silly little thought loops that are now safely sealed away. Stare out at the water. Notice how your brain refuses to accept the vastness of the sea, always focuses on a small part instead- a nearby wave breaking and rumbling, the scratch of salt on your lips and fingertips, the shifting shingle slipping between your toes. Walk towards a horizon you will never reach. Throw your flotsam to the tides, donate your used memories to the waves. Plastic bags will become jellyfish drifting apart like the desiccated atoms in your body or societies faced with environmental collapse. In a fun way, I like to think of my rubbish as my greatest legacy, it will out live my skin and my species by thousands of years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stage 3&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the sand, everything is liminal including your temporary body. I like to believe I will live forever but I hold up my hand, notice for the first time my fingers are made from wave foam. I can see veins laced with micro beads and polymer strands. The hairs on my wrists are small sticks of coral bleaching in the sun and the heat. I have nothing left to discard. I have emptied myself into the deepest trench and now float, star-fished on the surface. Churches balanced on cliffs will soon collapse. Lying in the water seems as good a place as any to observe the slow erosion of everything we have built. I untether my body, allow my limbs to drift in unseen currents towards an uncertain destination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s it! Enjoy your new decluttered life.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Churn</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-02-06-Churn/" />
    <updated>2024-02-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-02-06-Churn/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2024/churn.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: Beneath melancholy distorted joy/the complex emotions/shift constantly &quot; title=&quot;everything at the same time&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erasure poem taken from &lt;em&gt;Crack Magazine&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Manifesto for Art as Self Care</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-01-25-Manifesto-for-art-as-Self-Care/" />
    <updated>2024-01-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-01-25-Manifesto-for-art-as-Self-Care/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been thinking a lot about creative &#39;rules&#39; and how arbituary they are. As it&#39;s the new year, I&#39;ve been wondering where I want to take my poetry and my creativity and have decided I want to do it for its own sake. I want to focus more on the wellbeing aspects of writing and making things rather than the end result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, here are some principles for art as self care:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Engage with a wide range of cool art from cool people. Follow your curiosity but also seek out new things and works you aren&#39;t aware of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Share what you like and write why. If you don&#39;t like things, make private notes to yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Use paper for thinking and playing, use screens for editing and refining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have a very small daily practise -less than five minutes. This could be a haiku or a quick sketch. Try to do it daily but don&#39;t beat yourself up if you don&#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Observe the world around you as much as possible. Concentrate on your senses. Write or sketch. Pull from these archives when stuck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Embrace &lt;em&gt;what if&lt;/em&gt;. Play with ideas and approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other artists have already made paths. Follow them for a while then branch off on your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seek collaborators and opportunities, not publicity or clout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Spend some time editing and refining your work, not to get it perfect but to see what happens if you improve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create for the commons. All art is an ongoing conversation, so publish with wild abandon. Remember it&#39;s no longer yours once it&#39;s been released.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&#39;t take comments to heart unless you trust the person and actively seek out their feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Finding Out</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-01-22-Finding-Out/" />
    <updated>2024-01-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-01-22-Finding-Out/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2024/findingout.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: By playing/our human senses capture/a rare glimpse into the cryptic world/ outside the temporal realm&quot; title=&quot;Screw around, find out, make art&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erasure poem taken from an interview with Merlin Sheldrake in &lt;em&gt;Good on Paper.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The forecast sighs</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-01-12-The-forecast-sighs/" />
    <updated>2024-01-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-01-12-The-forecast-sighs/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Amber and scarlet triangles describe&lt;br&gt;
the island. These winding lanes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;are dead screens. As I push forward,&lt;br&gt;
I am a lone faulty pixel in darkness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Puddles erupt in sudden static bursts.&lt;br&gt;
This night lies between number stations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I drive onwards, seeking the source,&lt;br&gt;
shell swallowed by the detuned gloom.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2023 in Review: Personal reflections</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-01-06-2023-in-review-Personal-Reflections/" />
    <updated>2024-01-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2024-01-06-2023-in-review-Personal-Reflections/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Once again I closed off last year and started the new one by filling out a &lt;a href=&quot;https://yearcompass.com/&quot;&gt;year compass&lt;/a&gt; booklet. Although the years are arbitrary, I find this time to reflect and reset immensely valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I did &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2022-in-review-personal-reflections/&quot;&gt;last year&lt;/a&gt;, I&#39;ve decided to also summarise the year in a personal way, as opposed to my &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk//2023-in-review&quot;&gt;rants&lt;/a&gt; about politics. It&#39;s reasonably long, so strap in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote late last year about my desire to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/slowing-down/&quot;&gt;slow down&lt;/a&gt; a bit, reflecting it in my review of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2022-in-review-personal-reflections/&quot;&gt;2022&lt;/a&gt;. I wanted a fallow year, to regroup and reflect more. For the first half of the year, I was reasonably successful. I had surgery to remove my gallbladder[^1] and as a result I needed to not do anything for a little bit. I was lucky to make a full recovery quickly, but the time off forced me to do less. Life moved on of course, and I ended up filling my time with more distractions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also moved to the countryside this year, which was a welcome change of pace. I&#39;m forty five minutes outside of Bristol now, which is close enough to go into work but far enough that I feel a little removed from the city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latter half of the year has been tough in a few ways I&#39;m not going into here, but it was healing to be surrounded by nature and to watch the seasons change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was lucky enough to go to lots of interesting places this year. Bilbao and San Sebastian were culinary delights, with incredible food and amazing culture. Bluedot festival was a lot of fun [^2], with science talks, comedy and excellent live music. I also spent a week in Cornwall for my wedding anniversary, watching the sea and reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although some things have been a struggle, I am lucky in so many ways. I am reminded of this daily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Writing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/on-submissions/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, I deliberately wanted to avoid submitting to journals this year. I took the pressure off myself and instead focused on writing poems. I aimed for one a week, which I didn&#39;t always hit. But that&#39;s ok, because I think I&#39;ve successfully reset my writing process, slowing down making poems and taking more time for editing. I&#39;ve also found a lot more joy and fun in the process itself. I&#39;d like to keep the attention more on the process of writing, not the end result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://notes.davidralphlewis.co.uk/books23&quot;&gt;38 books&lt;/a&gt; last year, a little less than my usual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Broken Earth&lt;/em&gt; trilogy by N.K. Jemisen was my clear favourite speculative series I read last year, with a wildly inventive setting and unique, well realised characters. Somehow, Jemisen manages to keep the balance between tiny moments of character and huge moments of world building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Close behind was &lt;em&gt;Black Sun&lt;/em&gt; by Rebecca Roanhorse, which is a fantasy novel based on pre-Columbus American legends. It also has excellent world building and a jaw dropping ending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other novels I enjoyed were &lt;em&gt;Tomorrow and Tomorrow and Tomorrow&lt;/em&gt; by Gabrielle Zevin, which is about games and the joy of collaborating with others. It avoids cliché and goes in some really interesting directions. &lt;em&gt;Our Wives Under the Sea&lt;/em&gt; by Julia Armfield also avoids cliché, lying somewhere between social realism and horror to create a compelling tale about grieving someone while they are still alive. &lt;em&gt;To The Lighthouse&lt;/em&gt; by Virginia Woolf was a reread, but I lost myself to the beautiful music of her sentences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wintering&lt;/em&gt; by Katherine May was my favourite non-fiction book I read, dealing with the necessity of rest and recovering from unexpected sad times, and acknowledging and accepting them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Poetry wise, I loved &lt;em&gt;Deep Wheel Orcadia&lt;/em&gt;, a sci-fi novel written in verse and in Orkney dialect. It was beautiful and profound, and completely unique. I read a lot of books by Bristol poets as well, with &lt;em&gt;The Nation&#39;s Saddest Love Poems&lt;/em&gt; by Sam J. Grudgings being sad, tender and only slightly horrific. &lt;em&gt;Faulty Manufacturing&lt;/em&gt; by Josie Alford is a brutally honest exploration of her complicated feelings after the death of her father, with end lines that absolutely cut you deep. Finally, &lt;em&gt;Health Hireth&lt;/em&gt; by Taran Spalding Jenkins is a pamphlet of lyrical beauty that explores myth, illness and language, with poems written in Kernewek and translated back into English.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think with all my reading this year the things I&#39;ve enjoyed the most have been doing something new or different, expanding the possibilities of language and story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An unintentional side effect of moving to the country was I listened to a lot more new music, as my commute into the office twice a week is the perfect time to stick on an album.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favourite album of the year was &lt;em&gt;Heavy Heavy&lt;/em&gt; by Young Fathers. It&#39;s an incredible genre hopping album full of surprises and twists and turns, sometimes rap, sometimes soul, sometimes choral unity. I was lucky enough to see them at Bluedot and it elevated the album for me, as live they are powerful and full of intense amounts of energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also listened a lot to &lt;em&gt;After the Magic&lt;/em&gt;, by Paranoul, which is intense in a different way, mixing elements of shoegaze and indie rock together to create a heady sonic mix. The production makes everything clear though and it never gets lost in the muddy sound the way some post rock stuff does. Jeff Rosenstock&#39;s album &lt;em&gt;HELLMODE&lt;/em&gt; was also a highlight, being pop punk songs about healing and improving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In quieter moments, I looked to &lt;em&gt;Does Spring Hide It&#39;s Joy&lt;/em&gt;,  a two hour cello drone album by Kali Malone. I found the extended cello notes to be hypnotic and mesmerising. A late entry was King Creosote&#39;s &lt;em&gt;I DES&lt;/em&gt;, a beautiful folk album about death and grief, with some dancier tracks. It&#39;s lush and beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other music I enjoyed includes &lt;em&gt;Radical Romantics&lt;/em&gt; by Fever Ray, &lt;em&gt;Integrated Tech Solutions&lt;/em&gt; by Aesop Rock, &lt;em&gt;Live at Bush Hall&lt;/em&gt; by Black Country, New Road[^3] and &lt;em&gt;The Record&lt;/em&gt; by boygenuis. It was a really good year for music and I hope to carry on listening with the same intensity. The more I explore new music, the more I find.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Games&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Legend of Zelda: Breath of the Wild&lt;/em&gt;  &amp;amp; &lt;em&gt;The Legend of Zelda: Tears of the Kingdom&lt;/em&gt;-  I spent a lot of this year exploring Hyrule. &lt;em&gt;Breath of the Wild&lt;/em&gt; is slower and more contemplative, whereas &lt;em&gt;Tears of the Kingdom&lt;/em&gt; is more frantic. Both games offer a rich open world to get lost in, full of detail and unique moments. Exploration is rewarded and you always feel like you are forging your own path. I explored almost every nook of Hyrule and enjoyed every moment of it. Truly, both games are stunning works of art.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also played a fair bit of &lt;em&gt;Fortnite&lt;/em&gt;. I&#39;m terrible at it but it&#39;s a good social experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also spent quite a lot of time this year planning and running a new &lt;em&gt;Dungeons and Dragons&lt;/em&gt; campaign, having wrapped up a heavily modified version of &lt;em&gt;Lost Mines of Phandelver&lt;/em&gt;. I&#39;m the DM and its a lot of fun seeing the unexpected ways sessions turn out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Looking Forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NVGuFdX5guE&quot;&gt;C G P Grey&lt;/a&gt;, I like setting themes for the year instead of resolution. Last year my theme was &amp;quot;A fallow year&amp;quot;, which spoke to what I wanted to do- slow down, reassess and find joy in things. I think I was mostly sucesssful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, I&#39;d like to build on that but not hermit myself away so much. I have a tendency to avoid the rest of the world, having mostly solitary hobbies like writing poems and swimming. I&#39;d like to strike a balance between resting, working on projects by myself and meeting and engaging with cool people. My theme for this year is therefore simply &amp;quot;connection&amp;quot;- with the moment, with my work, but most of all with others. If you&#39;re reading this far and you&#39;re a cool artist looking for a collaboration, drop me an email. If you&#39;re a friend, lets catch up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope the next year is good for everyone reading this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[^1]: All praise must go to the team at the BRI, for their care and attention. The NHS is such a precious resource, we must fight to keep it.
[^2]: It was also very wet and muddy, but that didn&#39;t matter.
[^3]: I also saw them at Bluedot, they were also excellent. I love how they have pulled themselves out of the ashes and formed a whole new experience after their lead singer left. &lt;em&gt;Turbine/ Pigs&lt;/em&gt; is maybe my favourite song of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2023 in review: Poisoning the Well</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2023-in-review" />
    <updated>2023-12-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2023-in-review</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;2023 was another year of unnecessary wars and suffering, with Russia and Ukraine rumbling on with no end in sight. Israel responded to a terrorist attack with maximum aggression against civilians, seeking vengeance against an oppressed population. It&#39;s hard to focus on the positives when the news seems so relentlessly bleak and when history repeats itself so frequently. Collectively, we never seem to learn the lessons of the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a government in the UK that is failing most of it&#39;s population. Inflation has gone way up and poverty is rising. This year has also been the hottest on record and the threat of climate change is no longer an abstraction. Here in the UK, it is now a reality and an emergency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of tackling any of these issues, or you know, leading in a crisis, we have a government who refuses to take any meaningful action. Led by an ineffective billionaire who doesn&#39;t understand the economic reality for most people in this country, this has been a year where politicians have decided to embrace the hard right. To distract attention from their lack of action, the government has attacked the most vulnerable in our society, launching attacks on immigrants, trans people and the poor. This year saw Suella Braverman call homelessness a &#39;lifestyle choice&#39;, while the government decided to demonise trans people at every turn and house asylum seekers in a barge with legionella. It&#39;s disgusting, using suffering people as scapegoats to distract from a government that is burying it&#39;s head in the sand and refusing to do anything meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The government has also decided to reverse restrictions on north sea oil drilling and signal that global warming is a woke myth. This is a major issue as the world stand at a crisis point. We need action, not denial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Tories know they will lose the next election because they have screwed up the economy. They are poisoning the well before they leave. Salting the earth so the conversation is moved away from any positive solutions. Theirs is a party lacking in any sort of empathy, and they are determined to corrupt everything with their hatred before they are forced out of office. Next year we need to kick the bastards out before they ruin anything more. Then we need to hold Labour accountable to be better. It&#39;s essential, not just for people who are suffering, but for the very future of our planet under climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mentioned at the start how hard positivity is to find when the news is so bleak. But we &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;/strong&gt; find it, we must cling to it like a life raft against everything. In &lt;em&gt;Hope in the Dark&lt;/em&gt;, Rebecca Solnit describes the necessity of hope against all odds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... hope is an ax you break down doors with in an emergency; because hope should shove you out the door, because it will take everything you have to steer the future away from endless war, from the annihilation of the earth&#39;s treasures and the grinding down of the poor and marginal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can&#39;t think of anything more necessary and relevant as we head into the new year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previous Years in Review: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2016-the-year-the-internet-took-over/&quot;&gt;2016&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2017-review-laughing-naked-emperor/&quot;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2018-in-review-a-poem/&quot;&gt;2018&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2019-year-of-contradictions/&quot;&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/so-long-2020/&quot;&gt;2020&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2021-in-review/&quot;&gt;2021&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2022-in-review-weaponised-nostalgia/&quot;&gt;2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Return to Me</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-11-28-Return-to-Me/" />
    <updated>2023-11-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-11-28-Return-to-Me/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Once again, you find yourself barefoot,&lt;br&gt;
toes buried in eroded stone, your steps&lt;br&gt;
hesitant, sinking. You stand at the edge&lt;br&gt;
of your island, listening to my breathing,&lt;br&gt;
the crash and retreat, the regular shingle&lt;br&gt;
sigh, the dance of a million small particles&lt;br&gt;
rearranging themselves in new patterns.&lt;br&gt;
The sun is already setting, elongating&lt;br&gt;
your shadow, making me shimmer gold and&lt;br&gt;
jewel tipped. You breathe in my salt air.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again. you have found your feet uncertain,&lt;br&gt;
untethered to the land you live in. You have&lt;br&gt;
been drifting like morning mist, over footpaths&lt;br&gt;
and stiles, your destination unclear. You have&lt;br&gt;
been translucent, with ill defined borders.&lt;br&gt;
So you find yourself in front of me,&lt;br&gt;
walking forwards as wind ripples your chest.&lt;br&gt;
I am cold but you stay anyway. I can feel&lt;br&gt;
each small leg hair standing surprised.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me take your burdens, the ones you have carried&lt;br&gt;
for so long now without realising. As you&lt;br&gt;
wade further in, let me hold your intrusive&lt;br&gt;
thoughts, your vague worries. Let me wash&lt;br&gt;
the soil and land from your skin. Float now.&lt;br&gt;
Lie on your back, starfished. Float.&lt;br&gt;
Forget all the regular thoughts and patterns&lt;br&gt;
you loosely define as a self. Let them drift,&lt;br&gt;
become diffuse and bob towards the horizon.&lt;br&gt;
Float now, forgetting who or where you are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again the sun sits and light fades.&lt;br&gt;
Once again you have to pull your limbs&lt;br&gt;
together, become something like a person,&lt;br&gt;
define the boundaries of your being.&lt;br&gt;
Of course, you can&#39;t stay here forever.&lt;br&gt;
Once again, you pull on wrinkled cotton,&lt;br&gt;
shock of small scratches over skin.&lt;br&gt;
With a sigh, I regift your problems to you,&lt;br&gt;
not solved, but buffed clean and polished,&lt;br&gt;
shining smooth glass. Return to me&lt;br&gt;
with anything you wish to bring&lt;br&gt;
more into light, anything you wish to define.&lt;br&gt;
I will be waiting here, lapping the land,&lt;br&gt;
speaking in susurrations to the sandstone and the shore.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lost the Path</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/lost-the-path" />
    <updated>2023-11-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/lost-the-path</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2023/reverb.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: Where are we?/ Echoes from nowhere are strangely comforting/ this place feels forever familiar.&quot; title=&quot;*Constant Buzzing*&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erasure poem taken from &lt;em&gt;Crack&lt;/em&gt; magazine, November 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Perseids</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-11-13-Perseids/" />
    <updated>2023-11-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-11-13-Perseids/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Briefly, over lightly settled night,&lt;br&gt;
tungsten filaments flame out.&lt;br&gt;
Sunk in owl hoots and the scratching&lt;br&gt;
of small claws on terracotta pots,&lt;br&gt;
we feel the planet spin below our feet&lt;br&gt;
so fast there&#39;s no chance for dizziness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Particles fizzle and burn in thin&lt;br&gt;
danger, flickering bright shock&lt;br&gt;
for us sat below to wish upon-&lt;br&gt;
falling, forgotten disintegration.&lt;br&gt;
My outer limits shiver distant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am cloud behind emerging stars,&lt;br&gt;
scattered galaxy visible only through&lt;br&gt;
deep darkness and quiet attention,&lt;br&gt;
diffuse yet bound together by gravity,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;like the meteoroids we meet yearly&lt;br&gt;
like my body, tumbling through voids&lt;br&gt;
clinging onto a small rock, only&lt;br&gt;
occasionally noticing that down is relative.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Better Now</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-11-07-Better-Now/" />
    <updated>2023-11-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-11-07-Better-Now/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A flutter of flame consumed leaves&lt;br&gt;
falls onto my crown, drifting embers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I breathe in lungfuls of wild fennel&lt;br&gt;
drifting from nearby fallow fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A buzzard&#39;s shriek echoes over clover&lt;br&gt;
reclaiming every exposed inch of loam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have so much time now.&lt;br&gt;
I hold it lightly in my hands,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;offer it to the churning sky,&lt;br&gt;
watch it flit away like a finch.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The news was cancelled today</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-10-20-The-news-was-canceled-today/" />
    <updated>2023-10-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-10-20-The-news-was-canceled-today/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;because there was no danger or threat,&lt;br&gt;
no unwanted developments. There were no murders&lt;br&gt;
because we melted down our knives and guns&lt;br&gt;
to build homes, schools and hospitals for everyone.&lt;br&gt;
War is now an archaic word, like famine&lt;br&gt;
or suffering. Climate change was solved years ago&lt;br&gt;
and every person has enough to eat and drink,&lt;br&gt;
has all the resources and support they need&lt;br&gt;
to thrive. Governments erased borders.
Money was always fictional, but now everyone&lt;br&gt;
acknowledges it. Of course, people still die,&lt;br&gt;
but it is never unexpected and always&lt;br&gt;
surrounded by those they love. We know
every human regardless of race, gender, religion&lt;br&gt;
or anything other difference, is a bright candle&lt;br&gt;
that needs to be cradled and we need everyone&lt;br&gt;
combined together to light up the dark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the news anchors stood up from their desks,&lt;br&gt;
wiped off their makeup&lt;br&gt;
disconnected their ear pieces&lt;br&gt;
and wandered out of the studio&lt;br&gt;
into the peace of the forest.&lt;br&gt;
Under an emerald canopy&lt;br&gt;
they kicked off&lt;br&gt;
their sensible shoes&lt;br&gt;
and felt soil and soft moss&lt;br&gt;
between their toes&lt;br&gt;
as dappled light danced&lt;br&gt;
for joy over their skin.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Sky Sunk</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/sky-sunk" />
    <updated>2023-10-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/sky-sunk</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2023/skysunk.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: Do Nothing/ Forever lost/ in blue&quot; title=&quot;This was an easy one, it just spilled out.&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erasure poem taken from gig listings in &lt;em&gt;Crack&lt;/em&gt; magazine, August 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Dungeness</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-10-03-Dungeness/" />
    <updated>2023-10-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-10-03-Dungeness/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Nothing grows here but sea kale&lt;br&gt;
and spite. We walk towards a horizon&lt;br&gt;
that refuses to get any closer,&lt;br&gt;
under the sun&#39;s pixelated glare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having no sense of perspective,&lt;br&gt;
I almost trip over rusting cogs&lt;br&gt;
of some unidentifiable machine.&lt;br&gt;
We are watched by a power plant,&lt;br&gt;
it&#39;s polygonal bulk threatening&lt;br&gt;
to heave and shiver. The brutalist&lt;br&gt;
structure is devoid of sound effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have noclipped into a staging area&lt;br&gt;
where broken textures are stored&lt;br&gt;
and defragged on repeating shingle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here is where the boats will land&lt;br&gt;
this glitched landscape full of errors.&lt;br&gt;
Here bodies will become headlines,&lt;br&gt;
become local gossip, become a way of life.&lt;br&gt;
And here is where people in wool suits&lt;br&gt;
will shove mothers, brothers and children&lt;br&gt;
back into the broken waves of the sea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really hope we get rid of this unusually cruel government soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Our Voices in the Chaos- now Free</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-08-29-Our-Voices-in-the-Chaos-now-Free/" />
    <updated>2023-08-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-08-29-Our-Voices-in-the-Chaos-now-Free/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In 2018 I was writing poems and putting erasure poems onto Instagram (much the same as today.) A small press called &lt;em&gt;Selcouth Station&lt;/em&gt; approached me and asked if I wanted to make a pamphlet around those erasure poems.  After a lot of work, the result was a hybrid pamphlet called &lt;em&gt;Our Voices in the Chaos&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I used the blackouts I created as prompts and wove them into my poetry. Often I would use the blackout as the first lines then write underneath, but I also use used them as the last line or a line in the middle. The poems were shaped by the erasures and tended towards surreal and vaguely apocalyptic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s strange reading it back now. The pamphlet was published in October 2019 and builds towards an imagined crisis. Of course, five months later we were in the middle of an actual crisis and it was nothing like the idea. The way I write poems has also changed a lot in the years since I published this pamphlet. I would do things very differently now and would probably get rid of half or more of the poems. This is necessary I think, because if you don&#39;t look back at your old work and cringe a little bit, you haven&#39;t evolved as an artist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, &lt;em&gt;Selcouth Station&lt;/em&gt; sadly closed down in March of this year. I really appreciate them for taking a chance on a fairly new poet and for publishing my work. They put care, attention and passion into their press and were willing to go along with my hybrid experiment. I&#39;ll always be grateful for what they did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the press gone, I&#39;m faced with the dilemma of what to do with this pamphlet as you can no longer buy it. So I&#39;ve decided to put it here for free. You can download it, share it, remix it, do what you want with it. It&#39;s no longer my work, it&#39;s yours. No catches, no newsletter signups (unless you want to of course, go &lt;a href=&quot;https://mailchi.mp/5643ab85b338/dispatches-from-david-ralph-lewis&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Just a free pdf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/books/Our-Voices-in-the-Chaos-free.pdf&quot;&gt;Download here&lt;/a&gt; (direct download, pdf only)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You are welcome to &lt;a href=&quot;https://ko-fi.com/davidralphlewis&quot;&gt;buy me a coffee&lt;/a&gt; but is by no means essential.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Reminder to Myself</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-08-23-A-Reminder-to-Myself/" />
    <updated>2023-08-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-08-23-A-Reminder-to-Myself/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you are reading this on a screen&lt;br&gt;
your face glowing cold and blue&lt;br&gt;
your hand reaching out across air,&lt;br&gt;
put down your device. Look around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice the wind rushing at your face,&lt;br&gt;
muddling and whipping your hair,&lt;br&gt;
numbing your fingertips and toes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have been falling for so long&lt;br&gt;
at terminal velocity it is typical now.&lt;br&gt;
You have grown acclimatised to seconds&lt;br&gt;
dropping into the nothing. You are&lt;br&gt;
rushing towards that same absence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try to hold onto what you can&lt;br&gt;
as you plunge. Grab moments;&lt;br&gt;
the mutating clouds of indigo,&lt;br&gt;
the emerald grass that grows and dies,&lt;br&gt;
dreams that flicker above your head&lt;br&gt;
like localised electrical storms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even here, even above the planet&lt;br&gt;
in the mesosphere, there is oxygen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Breathe.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Cloud Song</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/cloud-song" />
    <updated>2023-08-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/cloud-song</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2023/cloudsong.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: The sound was hungrily devoured./ What grabbed everyone was/ hypnotic extracts from the sky,/ frantic vocals captivating the air&quot; title=&quot;All the cool kids are listening to indecipherable yet somehow comprehensible messages from the sky in alien languages. Sound of the summer.&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erasure poem taken from &lt;em&gt;Crack&lt;/em&gt; magazine, May 23&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>As Above So Below</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-08-10-As-Above-So-Below/" />
    <updated>2023-08-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-08-10-As-Above-So-Below/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;0.2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mud as a river. Mud as a theoretical concept, the transistory state of matter rarely glimpsed. Mud described in complex equations. Mud as the consequence of our actions we refuse to acknowledge or take responsibility for, despite it chewing at our shins. Mud in our boots. Mud in our hair. Mud clogging up our pores so we sweat mud. Mud turning our hills to waterslides. Mud washing away our temporary shelters. Mud as a non-Newtonian fluid we can bounce across if we hit it hard enough. Mud as the inevitable future. Mud as penance. Mud as the herald, the herald of the flood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;0.6&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technical difficulties-&lt;br&gt;
Oh.&lt;br&gt;
Maybe if I-&lt;br&gt;
Oh.&lt;br&gt;
Or perhaps-&lt;br&gt;
Oh.&lt;br&gt;
Could you-&lt;br&gt;
Oh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1.1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ice receedes like a hairline,&lt;br&gt;
little at first then all at once.&lt;br&gt;
The problem lies beneath the skin,&lt;br&gt;
down under a mile of compressed blue,&lt;br&gt;
where strange bodies skitter and wriggle.
where pressure will implode careless bones.&lt;br&gt;
Down there, in the dark, it is warmer.&lt;br&gt;
Only by a degree. But pressure and salinity&lt;br&gt;
are poorly understood and difficult to model.&lt;br&gt;
And there, unnoticed by passing survey ships&lt;br&gt;
or penguins, tunnels are being carved&lt;br&gt;
into the glacier like delicate incisions,&lt;br&gt;
bringing warmer water to what lies above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1.7&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gulf stream splutters,&lt;br&gt;
croons to us like a drunk -&lt;br&gt;
croaking, hoarse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are held captive&lt;br&gt;
by its sporading warbling&lt;br&gt;
feel its hot breath&lt;br&gt;
rattling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2.5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just two morals before Rishi Sunak&lt;br&gt;
opened hundreds of lifespans&lt;br&gt;
for ommission and gasket extravagance&lt;br&gt;
in the north sea, an IT fishmonger&lt;br&gt;
founded by his fault-in-law&lt;br&gt;
signed a 1.5 billion binge death&lt;br&gt;
with enigma guilt BP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3.2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stand vulnerable under artifical rain,&lt;br&gt;
enjoying the luxury of not reading headlines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I count everything I know for certain,&lt;br&gt;
Watch it swirl and vanish down the drain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4.0&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the surface of this new lake&lt;br&gt;
hundreds of worms rejoice,&lt;br&gt;
then as water keeps cascading,&lt;br&gt;
twitch as one, stop moving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Section 2.5 was adapted from the first sentence of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thenational.scot/news/23697572.rishi-sunaks-family-firm-infosys-signed-1-5b-deal-bp/&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;em&gt;The National&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ambient II</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-08-04-Ambient-II/" />
    <updated>2023-08-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-08-04-Ambient-II/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;After Aphex Twin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All I conjure is the vertigo of ancient cliffs&lt;br&gt;
while listening to voices from the radiator,&lt;br&gt;
muffled sentences- &#39;rhubarb, rhubarb, rhubarb&#39;&lt;br&gt;
they murmur, a bad tv play. I clutch a hanky,&lt;br&gt;
concentrating on horizontal tree roots, the grass&lt;br&gt;
clinging to granite. I try not to think of the mold&lt;br&gt;
that grows logarithmically behind the curtains.&lt;br&gt;
My future is a distant ocean below, a grey blur.&lt;br&gt;
What is my life compared to weathered stone?&lt;br&gt;
Already my fingertips are mutating into blue calx,&lt;br&gt;
already my forehead is developing parallel stripes&lt;br&gt;
of strata. The decay inevitable, like shiny metal rods&lt;br&gt;
over thousands of years. This house will be a grey strip&lt;br&gt;
soon, our dwelling marked only by a mutated &#39;z&#39; twig&lt;br&gt;
growing in the cracks. Look, how worn the windowsill&lt;br&gt;
is already. I sigh to the silence, tracing a hexagon&lt;br&gt;
in dust. This world is not ours, it is owned by lichen,&lt;br&gt;
ours is only the shadow. We see reality in spots,&lt;br&gt;
in all those neglected corners, on the damp tassels&lt;br&gt;
of curtains. My body is indistinct, only a blur too,&lt;br&gt;
edges forgotten, bones crumbling to matchsticks.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Cacophony</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/cacophony" />
    <updated>2023-07-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/cacophony</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2023/cacophony.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: A slight chaos is obvious./ And what of that shadow/ either forgotten or lost?/Some different joy/ is out here screaming next to you&quot; title=&quot;LOUD NOISES&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erasure poem taken from &lt;em&gt;Gigwise&lt;/em&gt; magazine, issue 8 June 23&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Shhhh</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-07-18-Shhhh/" />
    <updated>2023-07-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-07-18-Shhhh/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Listen, in between these seconds&lt;br&gt;
plummeting like raindrops -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;away from your constant&lt;br&gt;
rotation of breath,&lt;br&gt;
tuning out a fuzzing&lt;br&gt;
whirr of fans, the growl&lt;br&gt;
of idling engines -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;behind it all, unnoticed&lt;br&gt;
the slow churn of a motor&lt;br&gt;
deep in the planets core,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and below, a cosmic bass note&lt;br&gt;
(the wheel grinding)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and distant still,&lt;br&gt;
beyond all that commotion-&lt;br&gt;
all the frantic cycles of our being,&lt;br&gt;
faint, forgotten -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the click of apertures,&lt;br&gt;
the scratch of pens.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>May and June 2023 Input</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-07-17-May-and-June-2023-Input/" />
    <updated>2023-07-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-07-17-May-and-June-2023-Input/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is slightly late as I&#39;ve thrown myself back into the world after a halting start to the year. I joined a gym, started going to more things and exploring the new area we live in. I also went to Birmingham and other places around the country a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the media I&#39;ve consumed in the past couple of months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Stone Sky&lt;/em&gt; by N. K. Jemisen - I&#39;ve gushed in previous editions of this blog about the first two books. This is no exception. I think it might be my favourite series of books I&#39;ve read this year. Jemisen expands the world once again, while deepening the flawed characters and the choices they make. It&#39;s a macro and micro approach that is unlike anything else I&#39;ve ever read. There are answers to questions but they are not what you would expect, and it all finishes with a climax that genuinely could go either way. I was completely and utterly bowled over by these books. Seek them out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Steal Like an Artist&lt;/em&gt; by Austin Kleon- I was completing the trilogy after years. It was odd coming to this book after the other two, as I feel like I&#39;ve incorporated a lot of this advice already into my creative practice. Still, it was good to be reminded about some of the concepts, especially in a year when I&#39;m digging into my practice more. I feel like I&#39;m going to keep coming back to this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;M Train&lt;/em&gt; by Patti Smith- In the first chapter, Smith is challenged by a dream to write a book about nothing. So this is a chronicle of her writing in cafes, but infinitely more interesting than that sounds. It expands to cover memory and life and everything inbetween. Smith is such an inspirational artist, full of passion and reverence for the creative act. I liked it all, even the diversions into tv mysteries I haven&#39;t seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Faulty Manufacturing&lt;/em&gt; by Josie Alford- A poetic exploration of grief that is at times funny, moving and painful. I know Josie a little through the Bristol poetry scene and this book is a fantastic evolution of their style. Each poem is pared by to just the essentials, with not an unnecessary word in them. Each final line is razor sharp and their is humour, sadness and anger mixed together. Recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Walking Towards the Noise&lt;/em&gt; by John Bowie- Poetry written during the pandemic, with sections called mask on, mask off, mask on again. I enjoyed a lot of the descriptions and individual lines, but overall this collection didn&#39;t quite click with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our Share of Night&lt;/em&gt; by Mariana Enriquez, translated by Megan McDowell- Sprawling horror novel across different times that parallels the military junta in Argentina. I liked a lot of this novel- the initial growing tension, the horror that unfolds from different perspectives and the complex, deeply flawed characters. However, I found that some parts dragged once the occult madness reveals itself, then it races too fast to the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Our Wives Under the Sea&lt;/em&gt; by Julia Armfield- A woman returns from a submarine trip which went on too long, and her wife is trying to communicate with her. I spent the first half of this book waiting for the weirdness to kick in and missing most of the subtext of grief and illness that runs throughout it. Partly there&#39;s some inertia in the story telling, but it kicks in around the second half of the book. The ending is deeply moving, in a dreamlike way and it is beautifully written through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Films&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Blades of Glory&lt;/em&gt; - A deeply silly film. Already now it seems quite dated, joining the ranks of other films in the mid 2000s that are based around a specific sport. But Will Ferrell and Jon Heder have enough comedic chops and charm to elevate it and make the most throwaway lines funny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Asteroid City&lt;/em&gt; - Wes Anderson has leant more into his style as his films go on. This is charming and of course, absolutely beautiful. For me, it felt like a collection of scenes rather than a coherent statement, especially with the framing device parts which don&#39;t add much to the film. But it&#39;s funny and unique throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TV Shows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;I Think You Should Leave with Tim Robinson&lt;/em&gt;- We binged all three seasons of this sketch show. None of the sketches goes in the direction you expect and it&#39;s endlessly inventive and quotable. Tim picks up on small societal irks and expands them to surreal proportions. It&#39;s brevity helps as well as each episode is only 15 minutes long, so it avoids the hit and miss aspect of a lot of sketch shows. I really enjoyed it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Theatre&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Ocean at the End of the Lane&lt;/em&gt;- Before this, I hadn&#39;t been to the theatre in a few years. This was a brilliant introduction back, which showcased what makes theatre special- the collective imagination. This production is stunning, using puppets and set changes to fullest effect. It&#39;s utterly magical at times, terrifying at others and works to bring the fantastical story to life. The acting across the board was superb- the lead actors especially acting young was impressive. What an incredible production.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s it for now, come back next time to see what I&#39;ve been enjoying.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Another espresso shot sky commute</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-07-09-Another-espresso-shot-sky-commute/" />
    <updated>2023-07-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-07-09-Another-espresso-shot-sky-commute/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I define myself by edges--my skin,&lt;br&gt;
car bonnets- but I am oh so permeable.&lt;br&gt;
Chest matching thumpthumpthump of potholes.&lt;br&gt;
Clemency lies between radio stations,&lt;br&gt;
in the pause before windshield wipers&lt;br&gt;
swish back to starting positions.&lt;br&gt;
Hands tapping morse on the steering wheel,&lt;br&gt;
messages to distant and unseen agents.&lt;br&gt;
My party trick is dissolving into vapour.&lt;br&gt;
Rumble strips and cat&#39;s eyes broadcast:&lt;br&gt;
&amp;quot;Forget all you know. Unlearn your old self.&lt;br&gt;
A new world is forming in articulated lorry spray.&lt;br&gt;
Rewild your petty dreams and ambitions.&amp;quot;&lt;br&gt;
Infusing clouds reach swirling fingers&lt;br&gt;
to stroke my embossed flesh, damp comfort.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>On Threads</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-07-07-On-Threads/" />
    <updated>2023-07-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-07-07-On-Threads/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;By now you would have seen there&#39;s a new social network in town. Threads is a Twitter alternative made by Meta[^1] and closely linked with Instagram. I signed up out of curiosity and almost immediately regretted it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I quit Twitter over a year ago because I found the signal to noise ratio to be too weak. My feed was being flooded with irrelevant information instead of people I actually follow. In the year since, I have valued quiet and going slower instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Threads has launched with an algorithmic feed by default and I hate it. Each constant refresh brings tons of irrelevant information from people I&#39;ve never heard off, all vying for your attention. It creates a feeling of overwhelm which I&#39;m sure will be very profitable. Opening it was like turning on a firehose of nonsense. They have taken the worst parts of Twitter and copied them wholesale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My main annoyance with an algorithmic feed is it defeats the point of social media. I want to see updates from the people I follow, not random stuff. Part of the reason I stayed on Twitter so long was the writing community, and I enjoyed seeing updates from people I followed through there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My other annoyance is deeper. I think a algorithmic feed is more anxiety inducing, more frantic and less likely to bring you calm. The twitch and pull of a constantly refreshing stream of in information is overwhelming and always leads to a sense you are missing out on something. I found I&#39;ve been a lot calmer by not exposing myself to random arguments constantly and not absorbing a thousand opinions at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment it seems like there is no good alternative. I don&#39;t want to shut myself off completely from the world. There are people I want to follow, events I&#39;d like to know about. Threads just isn&#39;t for me.[^2] I&#39;ll stick with Instagram, because its a bit more low and chill. Other than that, I&#39;ll continue to follow interesting people&#39;s blog and newsletters by RSS.[^3] It&#39;s a slower but more managable way of staying in touch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[^1]: So closely linked, I can&#39;t deactivate Threads without removing my Instagram account. How very annoying.
[^2]: Not to mention the various data sharing issues.
[^3]: * cough * My newsletter is &lt;a href=&quot;https://mailchi.mp/5643ab85b338/dispatches-from-david-ralph-lewis&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Elsewhere</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/elsewhere" />
    <updated>2023-07-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/elsewhere</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2023/elsewhere.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: You may decide to drift ethereal./ Become aware of the veil&quot; title=&quot;horoscopes really are a load of nonsense&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erasure poem taken from the horoscopes page of &lt;em&gt;The Metro&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Between them is a canyon</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-06-26-Between-them-is-a-canyon/" />
    <updated>2023-06-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-06-26-Between-them-is-a-canyon/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;They sometimes shine torches over the strata&lt;br&gt;
of compressed time, with sweeping, shaking&lt;br&gt;
hands. Eternity is present in their half smiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He carries a sadness for a long dead myth&lt;br&gt;
that he longs to bury in the river far below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She longs for a bridge in the same way you&lt;br&gt;
want to win the lottery but never buy a ticket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They talk in clouds that never quite merge.&lt;br&gt;
Unnoticed by them both, in the shadows,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a man sits at a piano and plays Debussy,&lt;br&gt;
the notes falling and fading into red dust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&#39;t a climax to a Nora Ephron film.&lt;br&gt;
They avoid eye contact. Later, she will text him&lt;br&gt;
&#39;I searched for your flashlight but got lost.&#39;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Night falls across the mesa like a stone&lt;br&gt;
bouncing off a cliff into the welcoming earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry to the people I saw who inspired this poem. I&#39;m sure you were having a perfectly nice time in reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was experimenting with consistency of images here. Not sure it fully works, but I liked some of the lines.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Personal Thoughts on Submissions</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-06-22-On-Submissions/" />
    <updated>2023-06-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-06-22-On-Submissions/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve spent a lot of this year purposely retreating from my typical ways of writing, to try and reinvent my practise. As such I made a conscious decision not to submit to literary journals or competitions this year. While previously I have had some moderate success, I found I was basing too much of my perception of my writing on how it was received.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you first start writing, there&#39;s no feedback. You need external validation to progress and grow your work. Submissions to literary journals are a good way to polish and improve your craft. When I sent poems out, I would give them a final edit to try and improve them further. Make them the best they can be. Occasionally, I would get feedback which would further help improve my work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem was, I invested my self worth in getting accepted. Last year, I submitted to 17 places and was rejected from all of them. Rejections happen, and the best advice I&#39;ve heard is just to be resilient, to keep going and trying. But for whatever reason, I found I couldn&#39;t do that and took each polite email personally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it&#39;s the difference between intrinsic and extrinsic motivation for art. Slowly, I had changed my reasons for making poems to an extrinsic motivation of journal acceptances, rather than creating art for arts sake. This is why this time off has been valuable, because it&#39;s allowed me to refocus on the intrinsic reasons for writing a poem and reassess what I think a good poem is. I&#39;ve gone back to playing more with my writing, slowing down and evaluating each rough first draft for what it is, rather than where I can submit it to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Halfway through the year and I&#39;m still not ready to go back. I&#39;m still trying to recalibrate my internal appreciation of what I want to write. I&#39;m enjoying throwing poems onto this blog and Instagram and forgetting about them. I might throw out a pamphlet towards the end of the year, I might not. All I know is this space has cleared the way for multiple projects I would like to create. It has been a good reminder that art can just be made for yourself and doesn&#39;t have to be published in any way at all.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I love walking in the woods so much I&#39;m going to change my name to Forest</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/ChangeNameForest" />
    <updated>2023-06-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/ChangeNameForest</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here, under the glitter of a multi-coloured canopy I am finding a new serenity, the peace of lives measured in centuries. I am removed from glaring lights and constant haze, breathing in a million micro-organisms. My pulse no longer has the twitch and shuffle of muffled drum and bass bleeding through the wall from next door, my heartbeat settles to the pace of my slow stride. I have left behind the disarray of the city, exchanged it for the slow drowning of moss. I am stopping walking, gazing up at the branches and the distant sun, falling faster. Recently I have been too much concerned with electrical misfires inside my head, I have forgotten to watch lichen climb a felled trunk. My toes are rooting into the soil. They are sending signals into the mycellium network. It responds with a sustained hum. This long note holds me captive. I breathe out poison, nutrients for the leaves encircling me. We sway in symbiosis. My legs bend together. Merge. Time is syrup. Here is stillness. My pulse is. Slowing. To a beat. per minute. Hour. Days dropping. Dead leaves. Pile. Mulch. Regrow. My skin now. brittle. Wrinkled. Bark. What was. My name? I am. reaching. Arms. Twigs. Arms. Branches. To sky. My smile. Frozen. My blood. sap. I reach. Up. Decades. Collapse. Sky. Branches. Reach. towards. Light. Light. Light. Light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another Bristol Tonic prompt (the title.) I had a lot of fun with this one&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Omen at Fishponds Junction</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-06-01-Omen-At-Fishponds-Junction/" />
    <updated>2023-06-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-06-01-Omen-At-Fishponds-Junction/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Down the central reservation he strode,&lt;br&gt;
unbothered by exhaust fumes or concrete,
face encased in a leather mask.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was idling in my ordered world&lt;br&gt;
watching gridlock for signs of movement,&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Lifeblood&lt;/em&gt; on my Micra&#39;s stereo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He stared at me, eyes covered&lt;br&gt;
by stitched holes, mine shielded&lt;br&gt;
by sunshade and plexiglass,&lt;br&gt;
raised a single finger towards&lt;br&gt;
the broiling, pyretic sky&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and marched onwards, message delivered.&lt;br&gt;
My spine became a melting glacier.&lt;br&gt;
I opened the passenger door, left&lt;br&gt;
my laptop and future on the hard shoulder&lt;br&gt;
as traffic crawled to the bear pit.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Shiny</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/shiny" />
    <updated>2023-05-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/shiny</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2023/shiny.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: We all need glimpses of hope/ surprise moments of calm/ delicate breathing&quot; title=&quot;Enjoyed destroying a silver marker for this one&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erasure poem taken from a random page of an unknown music magazine I had lying around.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Roaming</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-05-19-Roaming/" />
    <updated>2023-05-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-05-19-Roaming/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Overnight, loam has been churned.&lt;br&gt;
A fresh furrowed field before me.&lt;br&gt;
footpath now forgotten, land lost&lt;br&gt;
thanks to vast machines that chew&lt;br&gt;
and crunch, split fresh green shock&lt;br&gt;
into parallel mounds of uniform brown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a monarch still goes&lt;br&gt;
where it pleases,&lt;br&gt;
wings of eyes and flickering flame.&lt;br&gt;
Dandelion clocks, half extinguished&lt;br&gt;
persistent ground elder&lt;br&gt;
and carpets of clover&lt;br&gt;
still thrive on edges, under dry stone walls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wishing for lighter boots, I take a step,&lt;br&gt;
Press down petals and blades into soil&lt;br&gt;
when they yearn to stretch skywards,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;start a new desire line.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>April 2023 Input</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-05-16-April-2023-Input/" />
    <updated>2023-05-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-05-16-April-2023-Input/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It feel like this year has flown by. April vanished in the blink of an eye. I enjoyed being fully recovered and starting to explore more of my new home. I also got out a bit more and did things, so reading time was reduced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s the media I consumed when I was at home:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hello world&lt;/em&gt; by Hannah Fry- A book from 2018 about algorithms and how much they dominate our lives in different areas. I knew about some of it but a lot of this was new to me, especially in law and medicine. It feels particularly relevant five years on with the rise of ChatGPT and Stable Diffusion, but also already a little out of date. A good introduction to a complex subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On Mutability&lt;/em&gt; by Jo Shapcott- I was aware of the title poem but had never read the full collection before. This is lush, dense poetry reflecting on the fragility of life. I loved this collection and could have highlighted the whole book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Katabasis: Forking Through Memory&lt;/em&gt; by Saili Katebe - I&#39;ve known Saili from the Bristol Poetry scene for a while now but his pamphlet passed me by. I read it as part of a workshop where we all read it in silence then asked questions. The poems in this pamphlet grapple with masculinity and faith and feel intimate and personal, while inviting the reader in. It was especially interesting to me how Saili has adapted his performance style to the page, condensing and distilling his poetry. I&#39;d really recommend savouring this collection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Films&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dungeons and Dragons: Honor Amongst Thieves&lt;/em&gt;- I&#39;ve been running a D&amp;amp;D campaign for a year or so and this film captures the fun and chaos of the tabletop game. It&#39;s not revolutionary as a film, but everyone in it is having a lot of fun, especially Hugh Grant as the villain. It&#39;s what Marvel films want to be- breezy, funny and entertaining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Three Thousand Years of Longing&lt;/em&gt; - Tilda Swinton is a professor of narrative who accidentally uncorks a djinn and is granted three wishes. I really enjoyed this, it&#39;s a beautiful, slow meditation on the power of story to change our lives as well as a mediation on loneliness. It has some slow subtle touches and is well done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Polite Society&lt;/em&gt; - A delightful film that really commits to its absurd premise. Lens is getting married but her sister Ria wants to stop it. The film is told in an over the top way, with martial arts sequences and heists. It is a lot of fun throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TV Series&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reservation Dogs&lt;/em&gt; series two - I loved the first season of this comedy drama and the second lives up to the hype. It expands and deepens the cast, delving into some side characters stories. Ultimately, it&#39;s a story about how a community and individuals respond to sudden loss, and how they process the trauma afterwards. One of the best tv series around.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s it for this month. I&#39;m going to try and get outside more now summer is (almost) here.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>In these days of sushi terrorism</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-05-05-In-these-days-of-sushi-terrorism/" />
    <updated>2023-05-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-05-05-In-these-days-of-sushi-terrorism/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;second hand bright ghosts collide,&lt;br&gt;
lighting up our motorways in sparks&lt;br&gt;
of emerald and indigo. Disruption&lt;br&gt;
in the supply chain is our mantra,&lt;br&gt;
repeated often to become meaningless.&lt;br&gt;
Fish is mostly off the menu now&lt;br&gt;
hidden currents flourish incandescent.&lt;br&gt;
I barely think about my death machine&lt;br&gt;
despite piloting it twice daily.&lt;br&gt;
Watched by an arrogant pigeon,&lt;br&gt;
I flex my fingers, ready to push&lt;br&gt;
the correct button at the correct time.&lt;br&gt;
I have trained for this all my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An email arrives with a cruel squawk:&lt;br&gt;
&#39;Do your best. Fire is still needed.&lt;br&gt;
Please answer these questions asap:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How many sunflower seeds would replace your body?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How long until cargo containers become sentient?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What government mandated checks must you perform on each wasabi packet?&#39;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I throw another spectral log into the hearth&lt;br&gt;
watch it flicker like growing grass.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Recovery</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-04-27-Recovery/" />
    <updated>2023-04-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-04-27-Recovery/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Somewhere, possibly close, the kettle boils.&lt;br&gt;
I am waiting for my insides to knit together&lt;br&gt;
around an absence, watching petals a shade&lt;br&gt;
off clouds emerge on phalanx thin branches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;RNA is imprinted with memory, like lore.&lt;br&gt;
Most days I attempt to escape myself&lt;br&gt;
with bright lights and pleasant fictions.&lt;br&gt;
Scattered stem cells turn, united as one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naming is violence, so I resist identifying&lt;br&gt;
the birds that visit daily, just watch wings&lt;br&gt;
flash egg yolk, variegated vine, shimmering&lt;br&gt;
petrol spill; collecting seeds for longer days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From waterlogged soil, from the base of a cut down&lt;br&gt;
magnolia tree, I stretch towards an ink blot sky&lt;br&gt;
stitching out of sap a fresh spinal cord.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Flower Moon</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/flower-moon" />
    <updated>2023-04-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/flower-moon</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s Easter and all the daffodils are screaming&lt;br&gt;
at the awakening ground- &amp;quot;Lazy arsehole!&amp;quot;&lt;br&gt;
&amp;quot;Good for nothing useless compost!&amp;quot;&lt;br&gt;
Rhubarb cracks fresh bones as it stretches&lt;br&gt;
towards a terracotta sky, body on new body.&lt;br&gt;
The stillness you found among roadkill&lt;br&gt;
and in the cold and muddy verges&lt;br&gt;
has been shattered by sudden ferns.&lt;br&gt;
We have read the skies like scripture.&lt;br&gt;
Now is the time to live- breathless, unforgiving.&lt;br&gt;
I hold my unnoticed, selfish serenity close,&lt;br&gt;
feel it crack open, send out exploratory shoots,&lt;br&gt;
mutate into this fragile yellow dream.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2023 March Input</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/2023-march-input" />
    <updated>2023-04-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/2023-march-input</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the first couple of weeks in March I was recovering from gallbladder surgery, so had a lot of time to read and reflect and watch things as I let my body knit itself together. (I&#39;m back to full health now.) As a result, it&#39;s been quite a rich month, with lots to recommend. Here&#39;s what I read and consumed in March:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If All the World and Love Were Young&lt;/em&gt; by Stephen Sexton-A series of poems that merge Super Mario World with the story of the author&#39;s mother being treated for, and ultimately passing from, cancer. It&#39;s a beautiful collection where each poem takes the title from a Mario level, creating an odd juxtaposition. Contrasting the virtual world with the physical one is powerful throughout, and Sexton&#39;s control and play with language is beautiful. It&#39;s interesting to see a collection of poems take inspiration from a video game and is something I hope we see more of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Illuminations&lt;/em&gt; by Alan Moore-A collection of short stories by the former comic book master. I loved &lt;em&gt;Jerusalem&lt;/em&gt;, but wasn&#39;t as enamoured with this collection. There are some stand out stories- the eponymous story is creepy and lingers for a while, where others are weaker. In the middle of this collection is a novella, which sums up Moore&#39;s feelings about the comic book industry. It will surprise no one who has followed him that he is not a fan. It&#39;s infuriating as he using characters for his mouth-piece but then also wildly entertaining as it veers into surreal situations. A mixed bag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Obelix Gate&lt;/em&gt; by N. K. Jemisen - This is the second book in &lt;em&gt;The Broken Earth&lt;/em&gt; trilogy and continues the high quality. Jemisen picks up the story immediately after the first and complicates the world she has created, while deepening the characters and the situation. Tense and propulsive, this is brilliant writing that manages to be extremely strange and deeply relatable. I&#39;m reading the third book at the moment and love this series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Your Emergency Contact Has Experienced An Emergency&lt;/em&gt; by Chen Chen - A collection of poetry that is wry and sad, often at the same time. Chen Chen feels like the successor to Frank O&#39;Hara to me, which is no bad thing. He writes from a queer Chinese perspective, with humour and joy that is refreshing and unique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I Who Have Never Known Men&lt;/em&gt; by Jacqueline Harpman - I knew nothing about this novella going in and was blown away by it. It&#39;s a very strange book. Forty women live in a bunker and do not why they have been captured. The whole story is told from a detached, almost nihilistic perspective, and unfolds with the vividness and intensity of a waking dream. Recommended, but not an easy read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bless the Daughter Raised by a Voice in Her Head&lt;/em&gt; by Warsan Shire - This debut poetry collection from Warsan Shire is brilliant, confident and controlled, with poems that ring in your head for days after. It also hangs together incredibly well as a collection, with poems linked by different blessings and familial history. It&#39;s a powerful exploration of refugees, immigration and also Islam from a female perspective. I read it twice in row and want to go back again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anxious People&lt;/em&gt; by Fredrik Backman (translated by Neil Smith) - A rare book, full of laugh out loud moments but also humour and empathy. A bank robber takes people hostage (accidentally) and the police are trying to piece together what happens. Each character has issues which are never diminished by the plot, but explored and expanded on. It&#39;s a great exploration of anxiety, fears and what makes people tick as well as a plea for understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is How You Lose the Time War&lt;/em&gt; by Amal El-Mohtar &amp;amp; Max Gladstone - Epistolary science fiction novel dealing with two rivals involved in a time war. This is richly poetic, with most of the details of the world never explicitly stated, but available in close readings. It&#39;s unique in it&#39;s writing style, rich and lush and different to anything I have read before. I loved it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Deep Wheel Orcadia&lt;/em&gt; by Harry Josephine Giles- Another poetic science fiction novel (must be something in the air.) This is poetry written in an Orkney dialect, set on a distant space station far from the centre of the galaxy. Giles touches on issues of gender and national identity, while creating a rich world. The science fiction elements enhance the poetry, and the poetry enhances the strangeness of the situation. Giles also provides translations, sometimes merging three words together which creates a whole language of its own. This won the Hugo award and I can see why, it is completely unique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Films&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Akira&lt;/em&gt;- It&#39;s odd to watch this film now, because I&#39;ve seen so many other films and tv series that take direct inspiration from it. This film remains a mesmerising combination of detailed, beautiful animation and strange ideas, interspersed with overblown action scenes. There was a lot more body horror than I was expecting.  I enjoyed it but found it hard to fully engage with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TV series&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Don&#39;t Hug Me I&#39;m Scared&lt;/em&gt;- Originally a YouTube series, this is presented as a kids tv show with puppets where horror creeps in. It&#39;s weird, existential and powerful. I wondered how the short form would translate to longer episodes, but actually it gives them more chance to explore the strange world and experiment with different animation styles. Great, but maybe not one to watch when you are recovering from surgery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Buffy The Vampire Slayer&lt;/em&gt; Season 7- Our great Buffy rewatch, which has taken three years, has finally come to an end. The series finished really well, with the last few episodes being excellent. But the season is uneven, with too much time spent going over the same ground. The main villain is also pretty boring. A shame, but I have generally enjoyed rewatching &lt;em&gt;Buffy&lt;/em&gt;. It&#39;s a show that generally seems ahead of it&#39;s time, even if some parts didn&#39;t work out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Daisy Jones and The Six&lt;/em&gt;- A band that was popular in the seventies and is &lt;em&gt;definitely&lt;/em&gt; not based on Fleetwood Mac looks back on their heyday and why they broke up. Although this series hits a few of the rock documentary tropes, it&#39;s elevated by strong performances across the board, with each member of the band being complex and rich. The songs are also super catchy, and the musical performances are great. The series focuses on the songwriting process which feels refreshing. I really enjoyed it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s it for this month. I&#39;m looking forward to getting out into the world more.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Fever</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-04-10-Fever/" />
    <updated>2023-04-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-04-10-Fever/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I woke up in a thousand different realities&lt;br&gt;
simultaneously, head stuffed with cloves/&lt;br&gt;
industrial by-products and waste/&lt;br&gt;
a single sustained tinnitus buzz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My matchstick/ bleached coral/&lt;br&gt;
liquid mercury/ collapsing neutron star&lt;br&gt;
hands now heavy, lying limp on our bed&lt;br&gt;
of ball bearings/ tangled, knotted string/&lt;br&gt;
tulips ready to flower in the wrong season/&lt;br&gt;
©¢¥€&amp;lt;¦¦|÷™&amp;gt;|} / shredded rejection letters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I knew if I got up, I would be nothing,&lt;br&gt;
only a spectre roaming the cooling towers/&lt;br&gt;
sulphur clouds on the surface of Venus/&lt;br&gt;
the silent void/ an unlit, winding labyrinth&lt;br&gt;
deep beneath the earth that we will seal&lt;br&gt;
for ten thousand years, warn against entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your cool back of your palm to my forehead,&lt;br&gt;
collapsed possibilities, brought me back&lt;br&gt;
to our bedroom (/ flashing red lights.)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Liminal Spaces</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/liminal-spaces" />
    <updated>2023-03-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/liminal-spaces</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2023/liminal.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: This isn&#39;t mournful, he stresses/ these otherworldly sounds arrive defiantly./ Here, we are all aligned.&quot; title=&quot;Not sure what this one means either.&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erasure poem taken from Crack Magazine, February 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Almost</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-03-24-Almost/" />
    <updated>2023-03-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-03-24-Almost/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;and yes, I still gathered branches,&lt;br&gt;
and yes, I still wore my woollen coat,&lt;br&gt;
but it was unbuttoned, no scarf&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and yes, my skin still raised in surprise,&lt;br&gt;
and yes, the sky still heralded rain,&lt;br&gt;
but the sun was a paintbrush, not a scalpel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and yes, many branches were still bare&lt;br&gt;
but tight buds were gently unspooling&lt;br&gt;
and the grass rioted in damson and mustard&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and yes, warmer and more expansive days&lt;br&gt;
were diving towards me on golden wings&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2022-23 Winter Input</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-03-15-2022-23-Winter-Input/" />
    <updated>2023-03-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-03-15-2022-23-Winter-Input/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been meaning to do this for a couple of months, but during that time Christmas has come and gone, then I&#39;ve packed to move house, moved to the countryside and prepped for minor surgery. So no wonder I haven&#39;t had time to put thoughts to paper. I&#39;m settled into our country house now and the quiet is welcome. This is what I&#39;ve put into my brain from December 2022 to the end of February 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Sonnets&lt;/em&gt; by William Shakespeare &amp;amp; &lt;em&gt;Notes on the Sonnets&lt;/em&gt; by  Luke Kennard- I&#39;ve never read anything quite like &lt;em&gt;Notes on the Sonnets&lt;/em&gt;, which responds to each of Shakespeare&#39;s 154 sonnets with a prose poem. Oh and all the responses are set at the same house party. Sometimes Kennard comments on the language used, playfully pulling it apart , and sometimes he follows a theme to it&#39;s often absurd conclusion. Kennard threads the house party with recurring characters and motifs that come back, much like the original sonnets. I loved the fun of this collection and the surreal nature of the poems. Shakespeare&#39;s sonnets are also tonally weirder than I was expecting, often petty or jealous  and not always devotional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Make time&lt;/em&gt; by Jake Knapp and John Zeratsky- A bit like &lt;em&gt;Four Thousand Weeks&lt;/em&gt; by Oliver Burkeman but more practical and less philosophical. This is a guide on how to do more by doing less. The central idea is you chose one thing to focus on a day, call this your highlight, then block out time to really focus undistracted on it. It&#39;s useful to restrict yourself to one highlight a day, especially in this modern world where the temptation is to try and do everything. Some of the suggestions on how to achieve this aren&#39;t practical for everyone however and it assumes a certain level of autonomy in your life and career that not everyone will have.  Useful, but not essential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Radical Normalisation&lt;/em&gt; by Celia A Sohaindo- I read this why I was down with a cold, which maybe why it didn&#39;t leave a huge impression on me. The poems felt technically accomplished but I didn&#39;t connect with them emotionally.  Probably more me than the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Viaducts and River Views&lt;/em&gt; by Barry Hollow- I&#39;ve known Barry for a while through the Bristol poetry scene, so it was a delight to read his debut collection. I also read at his book launch, which was a real honour. These are poems rooted in specific places that are evocative and precise. Barry is excellent at experimenting with form and he plays with language artfully. Really recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How High We Go In The Dark&lt;/em&gt; by Sequoia Nagamatsu- A linked series of stories set after a global pandemic ravages the earth. All the stories have a mournful, melancholy tone as the characters attempt to grapple with the huge amount of loss. Death becomes a central part of society, with funeral houses controlling money and twisted rollercoasters being accepted as normal. I would have liked to have seen more of a variation in the various protagonists and tone of the stories, but the ideas and the way it links together are fascinating. Feels like the first modern novel I&#39;ve read that captures the feelings of the plague years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Coward&lt;/em&gt; by Tim Clare- An exploration of anxiety, both scientific and personal. Tim Clare suffers from extreme anxiety and panic attacks and attempts different methods in order to cure it. There is a lot of scientific research in this book and it has a tendency to get a bit lost in the technical detail, but the descriptions of his personal experiments to cure himself are engaging. Ultimately, it&#39;s a reminder that no one size fits all cure exists for mental health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mexican Gothic&lt;/em&gt; by Silvia Moreno-Garcia- A short novel that transplants the tropes of gothic novels to Mexico, then completely turns them upside down. It is a testament to how well the novel lays out it&#39;s clues and breadcrumbs that I didn&#39;t see the twist coming, but it made total sense. A fun, well written genre mash up, I breezed through this in a couple of days and found it really enjoyable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Fifth Season&lt;/em&gt; by N. K. Jemisen- The first book in the Broken Earth trilogy. This had me absolutely gripped. Jemisen writes so well about the impossible, bringing emotion and warmth to the magical occurrences that are just part of every day life. The world is rich, strange and unlike anything I&#39;ve read before, with it&#39;s own rules and customs that you absolutely believe. At the same time, Jemisen manages to make the characters unique, interesting and flawed. I raced through this book and immediately wanted to read the others in the series. Between this and &lt;em&gt;The City We Became&lt;/em&gt;, Jemisen is quickly becoming my favourite modern speculative author.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rain&lt;/em&gt; by Don Paterson- A technically stunning series of poems with an undercurrent of despair and existential doubt. Paterson makes form and rhyme seems effortless, with a unique perspective.. At the same time, I would have liked some of the poems to loosen up just a little as something seemed to be held back across the collection. I liked it, but wasn&#39;t completely blown away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Films&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Encanto&lt;/em&gt;- Animated Disney film about a Colombian family with magic powers and a house that is alive. There&#39;s some surreal moments mostly based around the house and some explorations of intergenerational trauma which I was not expecting. It&#39;s mostly fun and enjoyable, but the songs aren&#39;t as good as &lt;em&gt;Moana&lt;/em&gt;. It being a Disney film, the story is tied up a little too neatly as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pinocchio (2022, Guillermo del Toro)- I wanted to like this a lot more than I did. I generally love del Toro&#39;s films, but I found his more adult take on Pinocchio a bit lacking. The stop motion animation is beautiful, and there&#39;s a sequence set in a fascist training camp that almost justifies the film, but I found it meandering and unfocused. The plot is unable to settle on one moment for too long, rushing to the next sequence too quickly. A shame as there&#39;s some good stuff buried in here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Glass Onion&lt;/em&gt; - Broader and sillier than the first film, this is still a delightful skewering of the ultra rich and how they think the rules don&#39;t apply to them. The cast is having a lot of fun, with Daniel Craig and Janelle Monae being standouts in a strong line up. The mystery is satisfying, if not as twisty as the first film. I&#39;d quite happily watch a whole series of these films with the only link being Benoit Blanc solving mysteries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jungle Cruise&lt;/em&gt; - Way more fun than a film based on a theme park ride has a right to be.  It&#39;s an old school adventure film, the sort Hollywood gave up making in the mid 2000&#39;s. The CGI sequences are mostly forgettable, the plot is paper thin, but the cast are having a lot of fun, especially Dwayne Johnson and Emily Blunt. The script is also pretty decent, with some terrible jokes. It counts for a lot and elevates what could have been a fairly generic slog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Turning Red&lt;/em&gt;- A 13 year old with overbearing parents turns into a giant red panda at emotional moments. It&#39;s a big old metaphor for puberty and growing up, but well done and with a core female cast that feels refreshing. The characters are unique and the story is a little predictable. As someone who was a teenager in the early 2000&#39;s, the fact that films are now starting to have nostalgia for that age feels a little strange to me, but I guess it was inevitable. Still, the animation is beautiful and the film is enjoyable, if not one of Pixar&#39;s best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TV Series&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Andor&lt;/em&gt;- Disney accidentally makes the best Star Wars vehicle by seemingly ignoring all the rules it had set. This doesn&#39;t really link into the main films, instead showing side characters that develop and change as the series goes on. It&#39;s about the bureaucracy and terror of fascism and when people start to resist, and as such feels way more adult and considered than anything that  was in the Star Wars saga. I was burnt out on the galaxy far, far away after &lt;em&gt;The Book of Boba Fett&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Obi Wan&lt;/em&gt;, but this is the best thing they have made in an age. More of this approach please, using an existing framework to tell more interesting, nuanced stories.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m going to try and keep this up more regularly. I&#39;m also going to keep updating this blog with poems, erasures and whatever I feel like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed reading this, why not consider &lt;a href=&quot;https://us10.admin.mailchimp.com/reports/summary?id=03000a56e1f0&quot;&gt;subscribing&lt;/a&gt; to get posts in your inbox?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lights</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-03-08-Lights/" />
    <updated>2023-03-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-03-08-Lights/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The sky and each moment expands&lt;br&gt;
as I observe it. I&#39;ve forgotten the season&lt;br&gt;
but the single layer of skin on my fingers&lt;br&gt;
remembers. I am an uncertain brittle being,&lt;br&gt;
standing under the galaxy, watching your sighs&lt;br&gt;
form the briefest of clouds. A distant owl calls.&lt;br&gt;
I&#39;m not prey, not tonight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am breathing in supernova, holding your hand,&lt;br&gt;
the slightest sensation separating us.&lt;br&gt;
We look north where no city sleeps-&lt;br&gt;
spectres dance on the horizon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had almost fallen to the lure of routine,&lt;br&gt;
let another day drift into faded obsolescence.&lt;br&gt;
How easily the frail shell can fail. Soon, knives&lt;br&gt;
wielded by caring hands will slice into my stomach&lt;br&gt;
and I will thank them. A series of chances,&lt;br&gt;
circumstance and confusion has led me here&lt;br&gt;
like every crumbling second.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh magnetosphere, fragile membrane protecting&lt;br&gt;
us from the void&#39;s radioactive onslaught.&lt;br&gt;
Dreams, untethered, pulse and flicker over the stars.&lt;br&gt;
My skeleton vibrates in time with the Aurora.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Fly Away</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/fly-away" />
    <updated>2023-03-02T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/fly-away</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am hauling all our rugs, books,&lt;br&gt;
house plants, our glasses wrapped&lt;br&gt;
in bubble wrap and old duvets ,&lt;br&gt;
all our memories neatly boxed up,&lt;br&gt;
every object we own all jumbled,&lt;br&gt;
carrying from the borrowed van&lt;br&gt;
into our new home. I am bending&lt;br&gt;
at the knees. I am judging the structural&lt;br&gt;
stability of cardboard to ensure&lt;br&gt;
our horde will stack. Tessellation&lt;br&gt;
is essential. My shoulders radiate&lt;br&gt;
like embers. Your nerves are glowing&lt;br&gt;
filaments of thin tungsten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In bone branches above our heads,&lt;br&gt;
a welcoming committee of starlings land.&lt;br&gt;
We watch the tree fill with wings.&lt;br&gt;
For a moment, there is nothing&lt;br&gt;
separating us and the murmuration,&lt;br&gt;
all the voice that sing to the dizzying blue,&lt;br&gt;
calling in one rippling, multi harmonic, chittering&lt;br&gt;
warming song that echoes and shimmers and writhes&lt;br&gt;
and separates and shimmers and echoes again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You take my hand. One small body leaps&lt;br&gt;
and falls upwards, soars up, up into&lt;br&gt;
the vastness. We are too heavy,&lt;br&gt;
too landlocked for flight.&lt;br&gt;
So we watch it become invisible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, too, is an act of devotion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks again to &lt;em&gt;Bristol Tonic&lt;/em&gt; for the chance to write something new. My prompt this time was &#39;Fly away with me&#39;, which coincided nicely with my life.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Revolution Will Biodegrade</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/the-revolution-will-biodegrade" />
    <updated>2023-02-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/the-revolution-will-biodegrade</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2023/rewild.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: What if you could make this nature new/ overflowing with movement and the unknown&quot; title=&quot;I don&#39;t make erasure poetry any more, I rewild newspapers&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Return your charade of a citadel back&lt;br&gt;
to the abundant soil, the loan from loam&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;now long overdue and incurring fines.&lt;br&gt;
Rewild your infrastructure, your houses,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;both parliament and domestic. Break bricks&lt;br&gt;
down into constituent concepts and allow&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;new buds to bloom where walls once crouched.&lt;br&gt;
Your bone marrow and personality quirks could&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;become fertile compost for the new world.&lt;br&gt;
These words, shredded, are rich in carbon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erasure poem taken from Crack Magazine, February 2023. This one really just developed from the erasure.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Part Time</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-02-09-Part-Time/" />
    <updated>2023-02-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2023-02-09-Part-Time/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I maintained the gears of the moon as a university job. On my empty days, I polished the levers, tightened the cranks and ensured there was enough oil to guarantee a smooth rise. At night, the company had a whole team on standby for the show, but during the day I was left alone with the machinery, inside a vast and echoing warehouse. My jobs did not take very long. I was a glorified security guard. Most of my shift passed in the staff room, deep under the surface, surrounded by the whirr and sigh of complex systems I could barely understand. I ate my tuna sandwiches, read terrible sci-fi novels, listened to music on my half broken walkman held together by duct tape and watched money for my studies crawl up in a ticker inside my head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I was bored, I would walk out onto the dark side of the moon. Of course, we weren&#39;t allowed near the sculpted craters, the mountains formed of foam or the ten thousand floodlights. I would hold my breath and listen to the nothing, lose myself in the expanse of grey and silence. At these times, I liked to picture myself from above, a dot, barely visible, less than a smudge, a single cell on an infinite, sterile petri dish. I always breathed out too soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every poet needs at least one moon poem.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Midwinter</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/midwinter" />
    <updated>2023-01-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/midwinter</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Fresh frost has visited overnight,&lt;br&gt;
morning shudders, barely starts&lt;br&gt;
Our fallow fields now writhe with blight.&lt;br&gt;
Fresh frost has visited overnight,&lt;br&gt;
We have lost colour from our sight-&lt;br&gt;
like fools, we hold hope in our hearts.&lt;br&gt;
Fresh frost has visited overnight,&lt;br&gt;
morning shudders, barely starts.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Dawn Chorus</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/dawn-chorus" />
    <updated>2023-01-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/dawn-chorus</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Blackbirds sing from the only tree&lt;br&gt;
left standing on land scrubbed clean.&lt;br&gt;
I am watching these buildings awake&lt;br&gt;
as hidden beaks and wings call to light;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Come, illuminate this concrete plaza,&lt;br&gt;
turn our pavements holy. Cranes&lt;br&gt;
and scaffolding will be brass statues&lt;br&gt;
dipped in the rising sun. There&#39;s still&lt;br&gt;
a chance for this deforested city.&lt;br&gt;
The long night is never forever.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Alchemical</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/alchemical" />
    <updated>2023-01-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/alchemical</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2023/alchemical.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: Fuelled by tenderness/ each repetitive life/ is reconfigured/ into something redemptive&quot; title=&quot;Almost destroyed the first letter with the marker, posted anyway.&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken from Crack magazine.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2022 in Review: Personal Reflections</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/2022-in-review-personal-reflections" />
    <updated>2023-01-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/2022-in-review-personal-reflections</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Following on from last week&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2022-in-review-weaponised-nostalgia/&quot;&gt;year in review post&lt;/a&gt;, which was more political in nature, I thought I would take some time to reflect on last year from a personal perspective. Each year I go through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://yearcompass.com/&quot;&gt;Year Compass&lt;/a&gt; as a ritual to close down the last year and set goals for the next, so this post is informed by that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s also long and quite self indulgent so strap in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2022&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, it was a mixed year. I was ill for a lot of it, with a bout of covid in the summer [^1], complications of gallstones and various miscellaneous colds.[^2] I spent a larger proportion of this year than I would like sat on the sofa doing nothing. When I wasn&#39;t feeling sorry for myself, I was very busy, a factor compounded by illness. I didn&#39;t do a great job of managing the stress and allowed it to get on top of me. The ongoing cost of living crisis didn&#39;t help either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s the negative stuff out of the way. This year was also one of the happiest of my life. I got married to my partner of eight years, and the wedding was such a joyful, brilliant day. We planned it together, did almost everything ourselves and it really came together. I felt incredibly lucky to be married to my amazing wife. We got to go on a honeymoon to Croatia, which was blissful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also travelled to Porto earlier in the year. After the two years of the pandemic, the world seemed to open up for us. Returning to live music was also a blessing, especially highlighted by an all day alternative festival at the Exchange which invigorated me and made me realise how much good music is out there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my day job, I was also lucky to get a promotion this year, which was very welcome. I feel like I&#39;m finally making strides in my career and feel more confident with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&#39;t write or submit a lot. A lot of my creative output in 2022 was typing up old poems or finishing off old projects, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/reality-adjustments/&quot;&gt;the game&lt;/a&gt; I put out earlier this year. I didn&#39;t do much generation of new material, which is what I would like to get back to this year. But where I think I became much more confident is in performance. I was lucky enough to be asked to perform at a number of nights, including Fen Speak, Open Collab and Barry Hollow&#39;s book launch. I feel comfortable performing my nonsense on a stage to a bemused crowd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s hard to sum up all the changes in a year. It seems like too long but also not long enough. But all told it was pretty good, where the world opened up more and possibilities showed themselves to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s more than I&#39;ve published about my life in a while so let&#39;s go onto my favourite media of the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read &lt;a href=&quot;https://notes.davidralphlewis.co.uk/books2022&quot;&gt;53 books&lt;/a&gt; last year, with poetry and graphic novels bulking out that total. It&#39;s fairly low for me, as the busy-ness meant I watched more television instead of reading. I have enjoyed logging my input on this blog though, and want to continue it going forward.[^3]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Four Thousand Weeks: Time Management for Mortals&lt;/em&gt; had the biggest impact on my life. It came at exactly the right time, when I was on honeymoon and wanting to take the relaxation into my life going forward. It&#39;s also affected my relationship to productivity and made me question my desire to do everything. I&#39;ve become more intentional as a result of the book and want to keep that going forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favourite fiction last year was imaginative and unlike anything I&#39;d read before. &lt;em&gt;This One Sky Day&lt;/em&gt; by Leone Ross weaves carribean folklore with a story about grief and loss. &lt;em&gt;The City We Became&lt;/em&gt; by N.K. Jemisin is a critique of H. P. Lovecraft and an exploration of gentrification. Both are delightful for different reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Poetry wise, Basho translated by Nobuyuki Yuasa and &lt;em&gt;American Sonnets for My Past and Future Assassin&lt;/em&gt; by  Terrance Hayes showed me what was possible within the constraints of poetic form. Instead of being restrictive, the haiku and sonnets expand in possibilities. I also loved &lt;em&gt;The Bible II&lt;/em&gt; by Sam J. Grudging and &lt;em&gt;Notes on the Sonnets&lt;/em&gt; by Luke Kennard, both of which are wildly inventive and push the possibilities of poetry forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Films&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I watched &lt;a href=&quot;https://notes.davidralphlewis.co.uk/films2022&quot;&gt;26 films&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Everything, Everywhere, All At Once&lt;/em&gt; was the clear standout, a film I&#39;m still thinking about months later. It combines humour, serious family drama and existential doubt with an overall message of being kind to each other. It&#39;s fantastic and I intend to watch it again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also really enjoyed &lt;em&gt;Top Gun: Maverick&lt;/em&gt;, a film that was far better than it had any right to be, surpassing the original in my mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other films I enjoyed were &lt;em&gt;The Sparks Brothers&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Prospect&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Nightmare Alley&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Glass Onion&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Games&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I played a lot of &lt;em&gt;The Legend of Zelda: Breath of the Wild&lt;/em&gt; last year. Its an incredible experience, a huge world full of detail that rewards exploration. Just under a year in and I&#39;m still finding new parts of Hyrule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a couple of years of solidly listening to ambient and drone, I returned to songs with lyrics and catchy choruses. Part of this was seeing some excellent bands live, partly it is shaking off the necessary calm of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three bands that stood out to me were Martha, Fortitude Valley and Fight Milk.[^4] All their songs have insanely catchy choruses and have been in heavy rotation throughout the year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://youtu.be/HDilMrddajg&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://youtu.be/rxSGFH1RD_w&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://youtu.be/iONqJoLfRLE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also really got into Sparks thanks to the documentary. Their collaboration with Franz Ferdinand, FFS, is funny, catchy and unlike anything else. Each band brings their own sensibility to the songs and the blend of voices works really well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://youtu.be/rCxLpte5loY&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I wanted something more sedate, I turned to Broadcast, specifically their album &lt;em&gt;Tender Buttons.&lt;/em&gt; This is beautiful, unique dream pop which somehow makes speaker interference sound calming. Sadly the singer is no longer with us, which is a shame as she had a stunning voice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://youtu.be/z79T8CUpksE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Looking forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not one for making big sweeping resolutions, preferring instead to have gradual change. I stumbled on the idea of theme years from C G P Grey recently and it describes what I&#39;ve been doing for a while- setting a course of travel, not an ultimate goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, I&#39;d like to carry on slowing down. I&#39;m moving to the country soon so ethat will help, but I&#39;d like to be more intentional and build mindful moments into my life. Try to do less, not more and rewild my attention. [^5] Leaving Twitter in April last year was a good idea, but I still mind myself in a twitchy loop sometimes. I&#39;d like to move away from that and into the real world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m also going to hold off submitting to literary magazines and journals, at least for a little bit. I&#39;ve lost my way with my writing and would like to write again for myself. I&#39;ve spent the past couple of years trying to write &#39;good&#39; poems, whatever that means, so I want to reset my own expectations for my practise and rediscover what I like in my writing. I might put some more poems on this website, but I want to hold off on submissions until I&#39;ve recalibrate my own sense of worth rather than someone else&#39;s approval. Art for the sake of art basically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a few other things but those are the main points. If you are still here, take twenty minutes out of your day to watch this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://youtu.be/jSrqC_angdc&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope the next year is good for you and there is joy in abundance. I wish you peace and power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ps Kick the Tories out please and thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[^1]: Third time, no fun.
[^2]: I don&#39;t know if not being around people during the pandemic has wiped out my immune system, but I feel much more susceptible.
[^3]: I will write up December 2022 shortly.
[^4]: Martha and Fortitude Valley share a couple of members but I think they are distinct enough to count separately.
[^5]: I wrote about this a bit &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/slowing-down/&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2022 in Review: Weaponised Nostalgia</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/2022-in-review-weaponised-nostalgia" />
    <updated>2022-12-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/2022-in-review-weaponised-nostalgia</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another year of political chaos, with three prime ministers, war in Ukraine and a cost of living crisis. It has been a lot.  Instead of returning to relative stability, the ripple effects of lockdowns have continued to have a huge impact and will likely reverberate for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s a phrase I keep coming back to which was included in an issue of the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.garbageday.email/&quot;&gt;Garbage Day newsletter&lt;/a&gt;- weaponised nostalgia. It strikes me this has been the defining imposition of the year, an enforced yearning for a simpler time that in all likelihood didn&#39;t ever exist. Politicians are deliberately exploiting this desire to mask horrific crimes, like shipping refugees off to Rwanda instead of allowing them into the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s influenced almost every political move this year. The Conservative party line is a return to normality now the pandemic is &#39;over&#39;, a shift to consume as much as possible and go back to growth. With the death of Queen Elizabeth II, the forced memorialisation reached fever pitch. The funeral felt like pomp and circumstance from a different world, a glimpse of Victorian tradition somehow featuring in the twenty first century. When Liz Truss &lt;a href=&quot;/resignation-a-coupling/&quot;&gt;resigned&lt;/a&gt;, there was even a brief period of time when the press were pushing a narrative of nostalgia for Boris Johnson, who had only left power six weeks earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The war in Ukraine could be seen through this lens as well, with Putin invading to shore up belief in the mighty Russian empire, which hasn&#39;t existed since the Tsarist times. Putin is using nostalgia to justify a brutal and unnecessary war, literally weaponizing it to try and claim territory that hasn&#39;t been part of Russia for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there&#39;s any good news in this chaos, it is that the tactics of the political elite do not seem to be working. The Tories have screwed things up so much the media has deserted them, This winter in Britain has seen the largest strike movements since the 1970&#39;s, a mass mobilisation of people resisting terrible conditions and pay. It&#39;s not just the pandemic or the cost of living crisis that have caused these strikes, it&#39;s twelve years of Tory austerity, it&#39;s wages not moving much since 2008 despite prices going up and it&#39;s the public services like the NHS being brought to their knees. Thanks in part to the government&#39;s greed and mismanagement, we are now entering a major recession and life for most people is going to be more of a struggle. The only Tory response to this is to cut services again, and not listen to the millions of people who are suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have had callous and cruel sociopaths in power for too long, people who treat the country like a personal  piggy bank, withdrawing as much as possible for their own amusement while never giving anything back. People are tired of the economy and the country being mismanaged. Even the war in Ukraine hasn&#39;t worked, with Russia not expecting so much fierce resistance from Ukrainians and being pushed back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the problem with using nostalgia as a weapon- it is only of limited use. Politicians pushing the narrative that everything was better in the past are ignorant to the world as it is. The pre-pandemic world has gone and now we need to deal with the new world, with all it&#39;s new challenges and contradictions. Instead of attempting to go back to another time, we need to face the world we are in with clear eyes and deal with the situation as it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s clear to me that our current leaders are no longer useful for the world we find ourselves in. We need new solutions. We need new systems. I hope in Britain and across the world we are on the brink of real, systemic change. Last year, in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2021-in-review/&quot;&gt;my year in review post&lt;/a&gt;, I concluded with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just hope we can keep the momentum going and demand a better and fairer world, one not ruled by the greedy, the rich and the self-interested but one that works for the most amount of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The glimmers of that better and fairer world are just beginning to appear.  It&#39;s hard to change a society, like steering a ship away from an iceberg. The turning circle is slow and wide. But I think things are turning.  This is the direction we need to be continually heading in, away from an imagined past that never existed and into a better future for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or alternatively:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://youtu.be/1_q_Iip8bRY&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previous Years in Review: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2016-the-year-the-internet-took-over/&quot;&gt;2016&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2017-review-laughing-naked-emperor/&quot;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2018-in-review-a-poem/&quot;&gt;2018&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2018-in-review-a-poem/&quot;&gt;2019&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/so-long-2020/&quot;&gt;2020&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2021-in-review/&quot;&gt;2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Suspended Animation</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/suspended-animation" />
    <updated>2022-12-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/suspended-animation</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;During the second spring,&lt;br&gt;
gorse opened exploratory&lt;br&gt;
canary buds, lending&lt;br&gt;
a perfume of coconut&lt;br&gt;
to apathetic winds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ground slept, twitched.&lt;br&gt;
A faint to forget&lt;br&gt;
the warmest year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I shuffle in enforced&lt;br&gt;
slow motion decay,&lt;br&gt;
rusty wool wrapping me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under the frozen pond&lt;br&gt;
scored with desire lines&lt;br&gt;
of dreaming crystalline-&lt;br&gt;
slight flutters, small hearts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see needles made swords&lt;br&gt;
spring slumbering under frost&lt;br&gt;
Buds now fading suns.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>November 2022 Input</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2022-12-09-November-2022-Input/" />
    <updated>2022-12-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/posts/2022-12-09-November-2022-Input/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;November rattled by. I thought I was going to read more due to the dark days and frost but actually I went to a lot of gigs and generally enjoyed myself. And here in Bristol, the frost only started in December. Here&#39;s what I did read and consume.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Brain-Dead Megaphone&lt;/em&gt; by George Saunders-  A collection of non fiction essays from Amercia&#39;s best short story writer, dealing with the banality of the media, how they appeal to the lowest common denominator as well as travel missives. What shines throughout all of the pieces is Saunder&#39;s humour and overwhelming empathy for fellow humans. There&#39;s an introduction to &lt;em&gt;Slaughterhouse 5&lt;/em&gt; in here and the comparison is apt, because Saunders is close to Vonnegut in style. Worth a read, but maybe not essential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mister Wonderful&lt;/em&gt; by Daniel Clowes- Short comic that plays off the format and style of Sunday morning comics. Instead of the cheap punchlines, we get a dense anxiety monologue from a reasonably unlikeable character who doesn&#39;t seem to engage with the world around him. Clowes delights in playing with the language of comic books, often placing thought boxes over dialogue boxes and inserting panels in different styles. There&#39;s a weird attitude to some of the wider social issues running throughout it, but mostly this is an entertaining read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ness&lt;/em&gt; by Robert Macfarlane and Stanley Donwood- Strange prose poem and illustrations dealing with Orford Ness, the abandoned nuclear testing site. It shows the natural world getting revenge on those whole caused destruction, in an unnerving way.  I loved the playful use of language, the overwhelming weirdness and the sense of place throughout this book.  It feels like a condensed version of &lt;em&gt;Annihilation&lt;/em&gt; in the best way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Roles we Play&lt;/em&gt; by Sabba Khan- Really interesting graphic novel about identify and religion as a muslim woman and a second generation immigrant to the UK from Pakistan. I got this out of the library and wasn&#39;t sure what to expect. The style is fairly unique, more of an illustrated essay than a story. The exploration of different identities depending on the situation as well as intergenerational trauma are nuanced and thought provoking. A unique read, but really recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TV Shows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Witchfinder&lt;/em&gt;- This is a dark comedy set during the puritan rule in England, a time the country would rather forget. Following a witchfinder taking a suspected witch to trial, it exposes the hypocrisy and self righteousness of middle England. It manages to be hilarious, with Daisy May Cooper and Tim Key stealing the show, whilst never losing sight of the misogyny and violence of the witch hunts. There&#39;s only six episodes, but it&#39;s one of the best comedies I&#39;ve seen recently.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saw three gigs last month and all of them were great in different ways.  There&#39;s something brilliant about being in a dark room singing along with strangers. Anais Mitchell was quiet, powerful and folky, in a small ish venue and a full band setup. Her voice is unique, plus she played songs from Hades Town (one of my favourite albums.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ijMnvVmkaRU&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next up was The Mountain Goats, which were in the beautiful Albert Hall in Manchester. Their set was polished and slick, with some deep dives into their 20 year catalogue. I got into them around about hte time they toured last, so it was really good to finally see them live. They didn&#39;t disappoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ztAjEgVEveI&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up last was Martha, a loud indie punk group with excellent sing along choruses. We saw them at The Excange, a brilliant community ran venue in Bristol. Each song was only a couple of minutes so they rattled through them, but their set was tight and brilliant. Well worth seeking out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1_q_Iip8bRY&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s it for now. I&#39;m going to do less as the year winds up, slow down and chill more. I might carry this on in the new year, we will see. I&#39;ll likely do a separate post with my favourite media of the year as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Unwrapped</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/unwrapped" />
    <updated>2022-12-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/unwrapped</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Her morning started with misty adolescent mooncore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She seized the day with runaway grawlix ballistic ghost wave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the evening, she was mystic salamander crooked puritan steam furtive caulk-hop&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He didn&#39;t really &#39;get&#39; music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It didn&#39;t last very long.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Slowing Down</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/slowing-down" />
    <updated>2022-11-24T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/slowing-down</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After I got married at the end of September, I went on honeymoon to Croatia. It was bliss- two weeks of lying on the beach, reading books and occasionally swimming. Now of course I&#39;m back to real life with all the admin and bills to pay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stopping for a little bit made me realise I&#39;ve been rushing a lot. I&#39;ve taken on more responsibility at work, organised a wedding and had covid twice in the last year as well as starting to run DnD sessions as a GM. Somehow, despite all this, I thought I could keep up my pandemic level of writing output, where I was writing three poems every morning, as well as updating this blog frequently while redesigning it.[^1]. Instead, I wrote much less this year and beat myself up about it. What submissions I did make were rejected, maybe because I was rushing to get them out.[^2]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I have more time, my normal response would be to double down and to try and write more. But I would like to bring some of that stillness I found in Croatia back to my normal life. I think instead of attempting to do everything at once, I&#39;m going to slow down and try to do less. I&#39;m going to seek slower mornings when I can, not cramming in writing, fiddling with this website, editing notes, exercising. Earlier this year I left Twitter and found that hugely beneficial, but I still get captured by the scroll of information on the web as well. I&#39;m going to try and sit in the discomfort of being bored for a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think creativity needs these moments of stillness and slowness. I was speaking to a poet friend who said they were too busy and had no time to write. And certainly in my life when I&#39;ve had big life changes or been busy with other things, I haven&#39;t been able to write. It&#39;s not about the time to sit down and do a draft, it&#39;s the headspace to actually process everything around you.  Poetry is a medium that demands slowness, both in creation and reading. It is one of the reasons I&#39;ve become so enamoured with it over recent year. I think in order to write it you need time to listen to the silence within, find out what&#39;s going on. So I&#39;m going to try slowing my process down for a bit and see where that gets me. Instead of writing three drafts of a poem in the half an hour I get before work, I&#39;m going to try to use that time to draft and edit one poem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partly I think this desire is seasonal. With winter encroaching the desire is too do less. But partly I think it is to be more intentional about how I spend my time.. One of the books that really changed my thinking was &lt;em&gt;Four Thousand Weeks&lt;/em&gt; by Oliver Burkeman[^3], which helped to clarify this desire to slow down. We all have limited time, the key is to use it with greater intentionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[^1]: I see now it was a panic response, attempting to document what was unknown and unspoken.
[^2]: Submitting to poetry journals takes a lot of work! Choosing poems, reading the magazines, formatting etc etc.
[^3]: My notes on the book are &lt;a href=&quot;https://notes.davidralphlewis.co.uk/4thousandweeks&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lost Levels</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/lost-levels" />
    <updated>2022-11-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/lost-levels</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2022/lost-levels.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: Unravelling in the uncanny valley/ a twinkling sense of unease sets in./ I shuffle into the landscape&quot; title=&quot;9087oihkjshhkkjh^%$??iugiu&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken from Crack Magazine, August 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>October 2022 Input</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/october-2022-input" />
    <updated>2022-11-04T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/october-2022-input</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was on honeymoon in Croatia for the start of October, so I relaxed on a beach and read loads of books. It was great. It got me back into reading a lot more. Now as it gets colder all I want to do is to hunker down with good books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s what went into my head this month:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Four Thousand Weeks&lt;/em&gt; by Oliver Burkeman - This is an antidote to productivity books that promise ways to do more with less time. There are no life hacks in this book. Instead, Burkeman writes a philosophical treatise on what it means to live. Our lives are brief and limited and at some point we will die. The antidote to this is to slow down, practice doing nothing and embrace the wonder of being alive. It&#39;s a beautiful, funny but also wise book that made me reassess my relationship to productivity and stop trying to do everything. Reading it on a beach in Croatia helped of course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Teleportation Accident&lt;/em&gt; by Ned Beauman - I&#39;ll admit, the start of this novel put me off, with it&#39;s unlikeable characters and jokes that didnt quite work. But Im glad I persevered, because this is a clever inversion of the historical novel. Instead of being caught up in significant events, the characters are always on the outside. It also takes several stylistic left turns I wasnt expecting and links together in unusual ways. Quite fun in the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lud-in-the-Mist&lt;/em&gt; by Hope Mirrlees - Strange Edwardian novel about a kingdom threatened by Faerie, the country nearest them that goes unmentioned. People in the town start eating Faerie fruit and the ruling class refuses to acknowledge the strange consequences. The metaphorical nature of this tale is not lost, as the fruit could be a stand in for sex or death. It&#39;s a strange, beguiling tale that has the pattern and language of an old folk tale, yet feels weirder and darker than any of those. I picked it up after reading a recommendation from Neil Gaiman a while ago, and it&#39;s clear it influenced a lot of modern fantasy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Waves&lt;/em&gt; by Virginia Woolf - Such a beautiful, powerful book. I hesitate to call it a novel because theres almost no plot. Instead, there are six monologues that weave in and out of each other. The writing is incredible, so detail rich and hypnotic in it&#39;s delivery. Towards the end it becomes deeply melancholic and overwhelming. This utterly blew me away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Good Listeners&lt;/em&gt; by Pascal Vine - This pamphlet is full of vivid, intense poems that feel deeply personal to Pascal while dealing with universal themes like compassion and spirituality. Theres a unique perspective throughout these poems which combine paganism, christianity and disability. Pascal is an excellent poet, conjuring vivid, unusual images. This is his debut publication and is well worth seeking out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Uncreative Writing&lt;/em&gt; by Kenneth Goldsmith - Interesting, if fairly academic read, about reacting to the excess of text that surrounds us. Instead of creating new works, the writer&#39;s job is to shape and select this text into new forms. Through unoriginal work the artist reveals itself. It was thought-provoking, but like a lot of conceptual art, the ideas seem better than the execution. I probably wont use any of these techniques but Im glad I read it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Keep Going!&lt;/em&gt; by Austin Kleon - A short book full of wise, useful advice about how to keep a creative practise going. It pairs well with &lt;em&gt;Four Thousand Weeks&lt;/em&gt;, being concerned with mortaliry and the choices we make. It also makes the case that the main purpose of art lies in the creation, not in external judgement, that you should make things to improve yourself, not to be judged. Nothing in here is revolutionary, but like Kleon&#39;s previous book &lt;em&gt;Show Your Work&lt;/em&gt;, I have a feeling I will return to this again and again to remind myself of the lessons within.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tv Shows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lord of the Rings: The Rings of Power&lt;/em&gt; - I thought this was really good. Making a prequel to the Lord of the Rings without having access to most of Tolkiens deep lore is a challenge, but I thought this was compelling and exciting all the way through, with excellent charactisation, world building and acting. It felt like Middle Earth again, with beautiful filming and attention to detail. I know people had issues with the lore [^1] but I thought it was a good adaptation of scant information. Adaptations always change things. Unlike my wife, I am not super invested in the history of the second age, so maybe I didn&#39;t mind the changes as much. I just wish they had given a small sliver of their massive budget to &lt;em&gt;Paper Girls.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cobra Kai&lt;/em&gt; Season 5 - Everyone&#39;s favourite karate fighting high school drama carries on for another season. This time, the ridiculousness tipped over from entertaining to overly silly. Everyone being obsessed with karate for some reason is fun; attempted murder and adults beating up children feels like its gone too far. I still enjoyed bits of it but overall I think the series has gone on a bit too long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Films&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Liquorice Pizza&lt;/em&gt; - I actually watched this back in August and had forgotten all about it when I did my last roundup. This film follows a fifteen year old entrepreneur and a twenty give year old woman stuck in a rut as their lives interweave. I wasn&#39;t entirely sure what to make of it. There are some perfect scenes but also a lot of padding. The ending also really feels incongruous to the rest of the film and marrs what came before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Suspiria&lt;/em&gt; (1977) - I watched this on Halloween, which feels appropriate. More than a standard horror film, this is a lurid nightmare scape, full of hyper-saturated lighting and intense, otherworldly music. Its all the better for being strange, striking its own style that is unlike anything else. I loved it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Podcasts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Magnus Archives&lt;/em&gt; - I finally got through all 200 episodes of this horror podcast. It starts as an episodic anthology but quickly evolves into something more. The last season is powerful and intense, with an ending that works really well. Its exceptionally well done, with excellent voice acting, creepy soundscapes and tight writing that makes the most of the audio format. Plus, there&#39;s another three seasons on the way!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s it for October. As the seasons slow down, I&#39;m going to try and do the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[^1]: Plus other racist bullshit we arent going into here.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>October&#39;s Oxidation</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/octobers-oxidation" />
    <updated>2022-10-27T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/octobers-oxidation</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Drains are clogged with circuit boards again.&lt;br&gt;
Flurries of rust flakes carpet the streets.&lt;br&gt;
All the air tastes of wet pennies. Every&lt;br&gt;
polished gear and lever is corroding fast&lt;br&gt;
under the pressures of time. Gutters, pipes&lt;br&gt;
peel off houses and droop. Children swing&lt;br&gt;
rivets on strings, laugh in modem screeches.&lt;br&gt;
Pull on your coat. Leave the Geiger counter&lt;br&gt;
on the kitchen side. Let&#39;s walk together,&lt;br&gt;
despite this antifreeze rain, feel the crunch&lt;br&gt;
and pop of ball bearings beneath our feet.&lt;br&gt;
Down in the landfill, bottles of bleach&lt;br&gt;
are waiting for spring to erupt and bloom.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Resignation- A Coupling</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/resignation-a-coupling" />
    <updated>2022-10-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/resignation-a-coupling</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I came into office&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;because in my possession was an ancient grimoire,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
at a time of great economic and international instability&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;from which a few will profit, the system working as it should.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Families and businesses were worried about&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;being suspended over a bottomless chasm with sharp teeth;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
about how to pay their bills;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;about flesh chewed down by ice, no help forthcoming.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putin&#39;s illegal war in Ukraine threatens the security&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;of our supply lines and our profit margins&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
of our whole continent.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;We do not think about those huddled in shelled buildings.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
And our country has been&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;a playground for rich fools dabbling in the occult&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
held back for too long by low economic growth.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;All hail eternal expansion, the flame that never flickers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was elected by the Conservative Party with&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;an ancient Sumerian chant, goat&#39;s blood and hemgrove, told to recite&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
a mandate to change&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;reality itself, if read in the right order, just like&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
this. We delivered on energy bills,&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;ensuring we had bodies for the pyres&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
and on cutting National Insurance.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The abyss gurgled with joy. We praised the great devourer.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
And we set out a vision for a&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;time when the ancient ones would roam freely, summoning a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
low-tax, high-growth economy that would take advantage of&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;our weary and beaten population. How many will we sacrifice to gain&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
the freedoms of Brexit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recognise, though, given the situation,&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;our rituals were ineffective. We were so certain.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
I cannot deliver the mandate on which I was elected&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;because the stars have grown cold, destroyed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
by the Conservative Party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have therefore spoken to His Majesty&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Mammon, the destroyer, the hungry void and&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
the King&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;of all that lies below&lt;/em&gt;,&lt;br&gt;
to notify him that I am&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;merely a sack of skin hollowed by atrocities, so I am&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
resigning as leader of the Conservative Party.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I preached consumption and was surprised when I was consumed.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This morning, I met the chairman of the&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;order, the high priest of the fearful&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
1922 Committee, Sir Graham Brady.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;I offered my neck in penance but was denied release.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
We&#39;ve agreed&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;to sleep in shadows, waiting the perfect time. We decided&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
that there will be a leadership election, to be completed&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;in the secret places where light refuses to tread&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
within the next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will ensure that we remain on a path to&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;feed on the rubble of a dying world, start the magicks to&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
deliver our fiscal plans and maintain&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;our connection to the great mouth hidden in rock, to sacrifice&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
our country&#39;s economic stability and national&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;stock of limbs and sinew, necessary fuel for our&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
security. I will remain&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;a squelching thing, a writhing mass of tentacles acting&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
as Prime Minister until a successor has been&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;pulled from the sucking mud, annoited with methane to become the&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
chosen&lt;br&gt;
&lt;em&gt;one to lead us into the eternal night.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Small Truth</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/a-small-truth" />
    <updated>2022-10-19T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/a-small-truth</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2022/truth.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: Everyone is infinite/ and whispering divine tender chaos&quot; title=&quot;Not just now, but always.&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken from Crack Magazine, May 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2022 August and September Input</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/2022-august-and-september-input" />
    <updated>2022-10-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/2022-august-and-september-input</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;September was almost entirely dedicated to wedding planning and admin. All our hard work paid off though, as the day was incredibly beautiful and full of immense happiness. I’m still overflowing from joy from the day, and had a relaxing, necessary honeymoon with my wife. It was amazing and still doesn’t feel fully real. I feel so very lucky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all the excitement I didn’t post one of these in August. So this is what I have managed to read and watch in the last two months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This One Sky Day&lt;/em&gt; by Leone Ross - Such a magical, funny and tender book dealing with the residents of Popisho, who all have cors, a type of magic innate to their being. It follows several different people throughout the book over one day as their lives intertwine and disaster looms. It’s often surreal with some incredible images, such as a black and white beach or someone plucking butterflies out of the air and eating them. But it’s always grounded in the emotions of the characters, whether it’s conflicting grief or desire. Beautifully written in a Caribbean dialect, this is a stunning book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;War of the Foxes&lt;/em&gt; by Richard Siken- I’m almost certainly going to have to read this one again. Complex, twisting poetry dealing with painting, representation and reality. I loved the recurring images and how coherent the book felt as a single unit. As it is so complex, I need another couple of rounds to fully digest it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tales of Earthsea&lt;/em&gt; by Ursula K. LeGuin- I returned to the Earthsea books after a break, the same way LeGuin returned later in life to the world. This is a collection of short stories that expand and complicate the world of Earthsea, changing the origins of Roke for example to be run by women. What I love about these novels is the coherent world LeGuin has built and the forensic attention to detail. You never for one second doubt that these are real islands, with real history. But also each novel twists and complicates your view of the world in unique ways whilst remaining coherent to the ongoing story. Looking forward to the last one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Use of Weapons&lt;/em&gt;- Iain M. Banks- Continuing my read through The Culture novels. This is a war novel written by a pacifist that exposes the horror and brutality of war. There’s a unique structure going on here and a twist that genuinely blindsided me. Unlike &lt;em&gt;The Player of Games&lt;/em&gt;, The Culture is seen from the outside and it makes them not feel so utopian. What elevates it however, is not the discussion of the Culture or the technology, but the in depth character study of Zakalwe. This is the series really hitting it’s stride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Films&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Palm Springs&lt;/em&gt;- A much darker take on the Groundhog day premise, where instead of attempting to improve himself the main character gives into despair and inevitability. It’s slickly done, carried by the chemistry of the two leads and digging into the rules of the looping world to provide a fresh take. I enjoyed it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Terminator 2: Judgement Day&lt;/em&gt; (rewatch)- For a thirty year old film (!), this still holds up. Part of it is the relentless pace the movie has, being three or four extended action scenes linked by the smallest moments of peace. Part of it is the effects, which still look fantastic even now. But mostly, it’s just a lean, well made film that knows exactly how to up the stakes and keep the tension high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TV shows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Paper Girls&lt;/em&gt;- It feels this came and went with very little fanfare or promotion. Which is a shame, because this is a really excellent adaptation of the comic books. Slowly the story down from it’s frantic pace, it has time to focus on all four of the main characters and to dig into what drives them. At the same time, it is a beautiful meditation on growing up and how your dreams and personality shifts as you get older. I just wish Amazon had given it more of a budget and allowed it to continue for another couple of seasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Buffy the Vampire Slayer&lt;/em&gt; Season 6- This is the season it all goes dark. I thought the exploration of depression was interesting and well done, but other elements like the Buffy/ Spike relationship and the magic as drugs metaphor felt clumsy and out of place. Tonally, it’s very different to the fun monster of the week show it started out as. I’m not sure it fully works, but it’s more interesting for a show to try something different than it is for it to stay the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;—&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s it for now. I have some plans to update this blog a bit more frequently going forward so we will see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>still</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/still" />
    <updated>2022-09-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/still</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2022/still.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: In the silence/ I am weightless/ lost in the clouds&quot; title=&quot;Shhhhhh&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken from Crack Magazine, August 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Oscillations</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/oscillations" />
    <updated>2022-08-29T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/oscillations</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2022/cosmos.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: The universe is flux/ unrecognisable between transformations&quot; title=&quot;Have you seen the deep field from JWST? The scale is mind blowing&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken from Crack Magazine, August 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>July 2022 Input</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/july-2022-input" />
    <updated>2022-08-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/july-2022-input</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In July I caught covid again, possibly for the third time. I&#39;m not a fan of this illness! But it did mean I suddenly had a lot of time on my hands to consume media, so this edition is extra long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Unbeatable Squirrel Girl, Vol. 1: Squirrel Power&lt;/em&gt; by Ryan North &amp;amp; Erica Henderson- Fun, whimsical comic with a stack of jokes on every page. I&#39;ve long been a fan of Ryan North&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://qwantz.com&quot;&gt;Dinosaur Comics&lt;/a&gt;, and this brings the same level of jokes and smart thinking to the Marvel universe. It&#39;s a palette cleanser of a book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Parable of the Sower&lt;/em&gt; by Octavia E. Butler- Let&#39;s read some science fiction to escape the world! Only this story is set in 2026 where climate change has ravaged the Americas. Oh. Powerful and hugely impactful, this is a violent, disturbing book. It&#39;s like J G Ballard but with much more empathy. What&#39;s interesting is how the main character views the situation she finds herself in as a slide back, drawing parallels to horrific aspects of history like slavery and war. Recommended, but not an easy read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mort&lt;/em&gt; by Terry Pratchett- Continuing my reread of the Discworld books, this is the first classic in the series. Telling the story of death&#39;s apprentice, this is hilarious but also tender, examining human foibles through the lens of Death, one of the greatest characters on the Disc. I thought I knew this particularly well, as I even was part of a stage adaptation in school, but the book surprised and delighted me in the re-read, being much more profound and concerned with mortality than I remembered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/em&gt; by James Clear- I appreciated some of the central findings of this book, lile how to implemeny better habits, but its not much spread thin over the pages. Something about the hussle bro tone of the book really rubs me up the wrong way as well. I wish I&#39;d just read a summary instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eve&lt;/em&gt; by Una-Another book dealing with climate change which I really did not need on the hottest day on record. This is a society in decline, drawing on both the rise of facism and the rise of the oceans to tell a nightmarish future version of the UK. The setting however, is much more interesting than the telling. The story fizzles out a little and the art seems half drawn at times. Interesting but not necessarily one to recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Violent Cases&lt;/em&gt; by Neil Gaiman &amp;amp; Dave McKean- Similar to &lt;em&gt;Eve&lt;/em&gt;, this has a lot of interesting ideas threaded out but is let down by the execution. It&#39;s Neil Gaiman&#39;s first graphic novel and it shows. Concerned with memory and threats you learn as a child but only understand as an adult, the art by Dave McKean is fantastic and unique. However, the story meanders somewhat and feels slight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Earthworks&lt;/em&gt; by Stewart Carswell- Poetry rooted in the land and history of England. This is a fascinating collection, delving into history and myth while resisting nationalism. Stewart&#39;s poetry is also lyrical and beautiful, dealing with deep time and the present with a deft touch. Recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Sandman #4: Season of Mists&lt;/em&gt; by Neil Gaiman, Matt Wagner, George Pratt, Dick Giordano, Kelley Jones, P. Craig Russell, Mike Dringenber &amp;amp; Malcolm Jones III- Re-reading Sandman before the television series. This is spectacular and so much fun. Every time I go back to The Sandman series I find something new. This time its the delight in all the deities gathered to seize control of hell and the subtle backgrounding of the issues with the endless. Mostly though what is a delight is the confidence in which the story is told. We know where the story is going, but twists like the non confrontation with Lucifer show a new side to the story. Such a good series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Paper Girls (volumes 1 - 6)&lt;/em&gt; by Brian K. Vaughan, Cliff Chiang, Matt Wilson &amp;amp; Jared K. Fletcher - This was also a re-read before watching the television series on Amazon. I had read volumes 1 -4 before, but this time I read the whole series in just a few days. Reading it together shows what a coherent and well done story it is. Telling the story of four paper girls from 1988 travelling in time, it is outlandish and over the top. The series uses full page panels to great effect, often lingering on strange and unusual images. But what is so brilliant about this series is not all the time travel and dinosaurs, but the focus on the characters and their struggles to grow up in a world that doesn&#39;t understand them and continually undermines them. It reminds me of the tv show &lt;em&gt;Dark&lt;/em&gt; in the best way, a complex story that fits together like a puzzle but ultimately is about the characters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Films&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sound of Metal&lt;/em&gt;- Riz Ahmed plays a drummer in a metal band who suffers sudden hearing loss and ends up in a community for deaf adults. Its an incredible character portrait that is immensely sympathetic to everyone in the story. Its also a slow unfolding tragedy. Beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;20 feet from stardom&lt;/em&gt; -Really interesting documentary about backing singers in famous bands and how they are constatly overlooked. The film mostly lets the singers speak for themselves, but resists any definitive conclusions. Even so, the music industry does not come accross well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thor: Love and Thunder&lt;/em&gt;- I really enjoyed &lt;em&gt;Thor: Ragnarok&lt;/em&gt;, but this is disappointing. The story feels empty, theres a constant joking tone that is ad odds with the serious subject matter but not in a good way. It feels lazy and by the numbers, especially compared to something so full of life like Ms Marvel. A rare miss from Taika Waititi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Tv series&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ms Marvel: Season 1&lt;/em&gt;- A shot of fresh air into the MCU. Ms Marvel feels much more grounded in day to day life and family history, as well as having the parition of india and Pakistan as a key story beat. It is funny and charming throughout. As always with Marvel, the villians are a bit weak, but overall this is the best MCU thing since &lt;em&gt;Wandavision&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stranger Things: Season 4&lt;/em&gt;- I really enjoyed the darker, horror inflicted tone to this series. It was much less focused on action and more on the characters. The ending was also a gut punch. The series really benefited from a worthwhile villain who impacted the story in a meaningful way. However, I still think many of the episodes were far too long. Like &lt;em&gt;The Marvelous Mrs Maisel&lt;/em&gt;, the Duffer Brothers need an editor or someone to say no to them. Still a pretty good season though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Other&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Critical Role Exandria Unlimited: Calamity&lt;/em&gt;- A four episode mini series of DND, this is some of the best roleplaying you will see. Telling the story of a collapse of a magical civilization, it has fantastic characters and brilliant, detailed world building. You know it&#39;s going to end in a terrible way, but the way it is done leaves you tense throughout. Recommended even if you don&#39;t know the ongoing &lt;em&gt;Critical Role&lt;/em&gt; campaign.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s it for this month. Probably won&#39;t read as much this month as I want to be out and about in the world, not cooped up with covid.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Gradient</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/gradient" />
    <updated>2022-07-20T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/gradient</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2022/gradient.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: Between the coastline&#39;s back and forth: Wave&#39;s crashing and existential freedom&quot; title=&quot;Back to this nonsense. I miss the sea.&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken from Crack Magazine, July 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>June 2022 Input</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/june-2022-input" />
    <updated>2022-07-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/june-2022-input</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Summer is here and I am wilting. This month I went out to a couple of gigs and loved it. I have missed live music, especially during the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also started a lot of things but didn&#39;t finish many of them, so this month&#39;s list is fairly short.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Sandman: Dream Country&lt;/em&gt; by Neil Gaiman, Kelley Jones, Charles Vess, Colleen Doran, Malcom Jones III - I&#39;m slowly rereading the Sandman series before the tv adaptation later this year. More so than Doll&#39;s House, I think these short stories are where the series really comes into its own, especially with the fantastic Midsummer&#39;s Night Dream. Morpheus is a background character in most of these stories and it is somehow stronger for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dungeon Master&#39;s Guide&lt;/em&gt; by Wizards of the Coast- I did read this, but it&#39;s more of a recipe book than a thrilling cover to cover novel. More of a reference guide but very handy, with loads of information and guides on how to run your game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Films&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Top Gun: Maverick&lt;/em&gt;- Way better than it had any right to be. One of the best heist films I&#39;ve seen, with jawdropping physical stunts. The story is predictable, sure, but it is also satisfying, well paced and well acted. It&#39;s a fantastic recruitment advert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Shang-Chi and the Legend of the Ten Rings&lt;/em&gt;- Marvel mixes it&#39;s usual formula with kung fu films and it works really well. It follows a formula sure, but having a director who actually knows how to shoot an action scene really makes a difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TV Shows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Obi-Wan Kenobi&lt;/em&gt;- The best Star Wars Tv show since the Mandalorian season one, but mostly because of Ewan McGregor and Hayden Christensen. There&#39;s some really interesting character work here but it&#39;s hidden under a lot of padding. It would have made a very good film but instead is a good tv show.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s it for this month. I&#39;m going to go enjoy the sun- or more realistically go outside for ten minutes and get burned.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Midsummer</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/midsummer" />
    <updated>2022-06-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/midsummer</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Our days are longest now, we hold the light&lt;br&gt;
solid between our fingers, like putty,&lt;br&gt;
before twirling, once more unstoppable.&lt;br&gt;
These are days we dream of deep in winter,&lt;br&gt;
when we are	banished in	eternal night.&lt;br&gt;
These are days suffused	with strange rare magicks,&lt;br&gt;
when our flame bodies flicker translucent.&lt;br&gt;
We manifest	what we will. Morning sparks&lt;br&gt;
alchemical. Our fingertips bristle.&lt;br&gt;
Play the music! Let us unite as one&lt;br&gt;
before the world tips inevitably&lt;br&gt;
back towards the shortening hours of sun.&lt;br&gt;
How precious these illuminated days.&lt;br&gt;
How soon, like warm embers, they start to fade.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>May 2022 Input</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/may-2022-input" />
    <updated>2022-06-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/may-2022-input</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;May went so fast. It was a fallow period creatively for me, I put nothing on this blog and didn&#39;t send any poems out. I hid away from the flags and jingoism. But I did leave plague island for the first time in ages and took a trip to Porto, which was delightful. I also met my newly born nephew, so a pretty good month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s what I consumed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The City We Became&lt;/em&gt; by N. K. Jemisen- What a book. This was a present for my fiancé, which she then said I should read. I&#39;m really glad I did because this book is fantastic, combining lovecraftian horrors with living cities. It&#39;s also a critique of gentrification and deals with racist systemic issues. I&#39;m really looking forward to the next book in the trilogy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Sandman: Endless Nights&lt;/em&gt; by Neil Gaiman et al- Stories of The Endless, written long after the initial, unparalleled run of the Sandman. I enjoyed catching up with Desire and Delirium, but the stories feel slight compared to the main run, side diversions from a bigger whole. Beautiful artwork though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Marketplace of Ideas&lt;/em&gt; by Stefan Mohamed- I picked this up after Stefan did a headline set at Tonic. Equal parts hilarious and bleak, this is poetry of the internet. I haven&#39;t read much that feels like it captures the current twitchy feeling of being online, but this does it perfectly. His voice is completely unique .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Convenience Store Woman&lt;/em&gt; by Sayaka Murata- Similar in theme and tone to Murata&#39;s other book, &lt;em&gt;Earthlings&lt;/em&gt;, this is less extreme but still compelling. Her characters have their own twisted logic that drives them forward, in opposition to societal expectations. I finished it quite quickly but it stayed with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Swamp Thing: The Root of All Evil&lt;/em&gt; by  Mark Millar, Grant Morrison, Phil Hester, Kim DeMulder and Tatjana Wood- I did not get on with this at all. An incoherent story that changes issue to issue, some weird art choices and panels that make it hard to follow what is going on. There&#39;s also some graphic violence for no reason as this is Vertigo in the 90s. Maybe I&#39;ll find the Alan Moore run instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Livestock&lt;/em&gt; by Hannah Berry- Grim satire about how celebrities are used as tools of power to distract from political events. The art style is bright and over the top to reflect this strange reality. It&#39;s funny throughout, but continually undercut with a sinister subplot. Written in 2017, this feels more relevant today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Films&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dr. Strange and the Multiverse of Madness&lt;/em&gt;- I&#39;ve seen a few people complaining about this, but I thought it was one of the better Marvel films. The horror elements are played up a lot more and that is where the film shines. There&#39;s also enough invention and unique stylings across the universes to keep it interesting. In the end though, superhero genre conventions win out and there&#39;s lots of scenes of people hitting each other. I&#39;d have liked to see it go full horror, instead of this strange mix of genres.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Everything Everywhere All At Once&lt;/em&gt;- The &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; multiverse film I watched this month. It&#39;s got absolutely everything in- hot dogs, kung fu and taxes. It starts slowly but ramps up quickly into an amazing, multi pronged story that manages to be hilarious, weird and also deeply emotionally affecting. Michelle Yeoh is also brilliant in this, playing so many different variations on the same character. Towards the end, it reminds me of the best of Vonnegut, using scifi to talk about the human condition. This is one of the best films I&#39;ve seen in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TV Shows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Moon Knight&lt;/em&gt;- Similar to Dr. Strange, this TV series is at it&#39;s best when it diverges from the established Marvel formula. It&#39;s fairly disconnected from the rest of the MCU, which I appreciated as the focus was more on this individual story, rather than an endless tease for what comes next. Oscar Isaacs has incredible physical and emotional range here, often communicating a whole new personality in a slight shift of posture. Although it ends in a superhero fight, I appreciate anything that takes as many risks as this series does.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s it for this month, take care out there.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>April 2022 Input</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/april-2022-input" />
    <updated>2022-05-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/april-2022-input</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I can&#39;t believe we are a third of the way through 2022. The tulips have bloomed and died back, warmer days are just around the corner. I haven&#39;t done a lot of writing due to life being busy but I did quit Twitter, so maybe in the future I will have more time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s the things I consumed last month:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Kids&lt;/em&gt; by Hannah Lowe- Another collection of sonnets. Something about the form means it is flexible for any subject. Here, Hannah Lowe uses the form to talk about children she taught, whilst also reflecting on her own memories and the wider political situation. I read it all in one sitting, wowed by the considered use of form and the love and humanity that shines through in each poem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Handful of Blue Earth&lt;/em&gt; by Venus Khory-Ghata translated by Marilyn Hacker- Three long poems, often surreal and laced through with strange surreal images. I found the section from &lt;em&gt;The Book of Petitions&lt;/em&gt; most affecting, but the whole book is great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Vanishing Half&lt;/em&gt; by Brit Bennett- This novel has several interweaving narratives, all centered on issues of race or &#39;passing&#39;. It is beautifully written, with characters that stay with you and a political angle that is never preachy. I loved how it flowed from one section to the next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This Fruiting Body&lt;/em&gt; by Caleb Parkin- Poems that reconsider humanity&#39;s relationship with the natural world, while mourning the destruction we have wrought. For all that, it&#39;s also witty and funny throughout, with more personal poems appearing towards the end. Pairs quite nicely with &lt;em&gt;Entangled Life&lt;/em&gt; which I finished &lt;a href=&quot;/2022-march-input/&quot;&gt;last month.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Films&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nightmare Alley&lt;/em&gt;- What a film. Guillermo Del Toro is at the top of his game with this film noir carnival tale. Everyone in this film gives amazing performances, especially Bradley Cooper who shows large shifts in his character without it seeming unnatural. It&#39;s also a tragedy which is rare now days, building to a shattering conclusion. I loved it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Adam Project- Ryan Reynolds in a time traveling fluff film. It&#39;s funny, with a good concept and breezes along quite well yet doesn&#39;t do a lot with the initial promise. The villain is just evil for the sake of it and it doesn&#39;t really go anywhere with the story. An undercurrent of regret and sadness saves it from being too forgettable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Sparks Brothers- I knew nothing about Sparks going in and this documentary is the perfect introduction. I loved how they didn&#39;t take themselves too seriously yet still strived to make art for decades. It&#39;s a love letter to the band, full of animation and gags throughout. I&#39;ve listened to Sparks a lot since watching this documentary and have had a great time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AfA4FphZHbc&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TV Shows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Buffy The Vampire Slayer&lt;/em&gt; Season 5- Much stronger than the patchy and cheap season four. This season fully dives into unique and bizarre mythology and it works. It&#39;s also decidedly more adult than other seasons, not in terms of violence or language but in the tragedy and trauma that permeates the action. It even tries to redeem Xander! (Spike is still terrible though.) I think I&#39;m at the point where I started watching when I was a kid, although my memories are fuzzy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Superstore&lt;/em&gt; Season 3- This is still a very enjoyable ensemble comedy, although it leans a little too heavily on the will they/ won&#39;t they trope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Marvelous Mrs. Maisel&lt;/em&gt; Season 2- Not as good as the first season. In my opinion, there&#39;s too much whimsy and not enough focus on the main story, with episodes dedicated to irrelevant details. The later half is better as it actually focuses on stand up comedy, but it gets distracted in the start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s it for this month. As I&#39;m no longer on Twitter I might try to post a few more things up here. Pretend its the early 2000&#39;s for a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What a Racket</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/what-a-racket" />
    <updated>2022-04-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/what-a-racket</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2022/racket.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: The synaptic impulses/of the machine/ loop and clatter/ convey interminable emotions&quot; title=&quot;Found some charcoal lads&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken from Crack Magazine, April 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2022 March Input</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/2022-march-input" />
    <updated>2022-04-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/2022-march-input</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;March was another busy month as I adjusted to my new job and did lots of wedding admin. I also prepped and published a weird little game/ poetry pamphlet about being lost in an everchanging city, which you can find more about &lt;a href=&quot;/reality-adjustments/&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s what&#39;s gone into my skull this last month:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I managed to read more than one book this month, but they were all by dudes. Oh well, will try to course correct in the next few months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entangled Life&lt;/em&gt; by Merlin Sheldrake- Mind expanding book about a neglected tree of life. Merlin makes the complex world of fungi clear and engaging, often bringing in his own experience to share his obsession. Along the way, he brings up fascinating questions about symbiosis and what life actually is. Highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;American Sonnets for My Past and Future Assassin&lt;/em&gt; by Terrance Hayes- During the Trump presidency Terrance Hayes wrote a sonnet a day. This book is a good refutation that form is constraining, as the sonnet frees up his poetry. Sometimes sad, often angry, this is a masterful collection I will be returning to often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wolf in White Van&lt;/em&gt; by John Darnielle- It&#39;s annoying when someone skilled in one area is great in another. Better known as the driving force behind The Mountain Goats, this is a melacholy, sad story about someone hiding from the world and the world seeking them out anyway. It&#39;s about the power of fiction and all the possibilities of life. There&#39;s not a lot of plot in the traditional sense but it&#39;s beautifully written and emotionally affecting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Narrow Road to the Deep North and Other Travel Sketches&lt;/em&gt; by Basho translated by Nobuyuki Yuasa- A mixture of prose and haiku, this speaks to me hundreds of years and thousands of miles away. I love the stillness and the reflection, the measured responses. Anyone can write haiku but these translations show that few can master the form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did not finish- &lt;em&gt;The Party and other stories&lt;/em&gt;- Anton Chekov translated by Ronald Wilkes- Started strong by the minutiae of life without a plot became a slog. I gave up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Films&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;You&#39;ve Got Mail&lt;/em&gt;- Tom Hanks and Meg Ryan swap emails and fall in love. Apart from the dated technology and characters continually surprised by the existence of the internet, I was impressed at how modern this twenty something year old film feels. There&#39;s an anti-capitalist message buried deep inside the love story as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TV Shows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Vox Machina&lt;/em&gt;- An animated adaptation of long running DND podcast &lt;em&gt;Critical Role&lt;/em&gt;. I knew very little about the first campaign going in but I shouldn&#39;t have worried- this is funny, crude and action packed, with satisfying arcs for all the characters. It uses action not just to look cool but to develop the characters. We breezed through it quickly and it&#39;s great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Superstore&lt;/em&gt; Season 2- American comedies always seem to find their stride in the second season. This is a much funnier season, with a strong ensemble cast and a surprisingly dark sense of humour. It&#39;s forays into worker&#39;s rights are surprisingly radical for a highly produced sitcom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s it for this month. Going to try and slow down in April, so I&#39;m not doing Napowrimo again.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>fragmented</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/fragmented" />
    <updated>2022-03-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/fragmented</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2022/fragmented.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: Sounds twist/ begin to congeal./The sky speeds/becomes scattershot/and restless&quot; title=&quot;I&#39;m not sure what about the design of this one but it was split down the middle so played around with it.&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken from Crack Magazine, April 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was delighted to be asked onto the Full House Literary Podcast talking about poetry and mental health. It was a thought provoking, interesting discussion that was quite wide ranging. Thanks so much to them for having me on, listen &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fullhouseliterary.com/podcast-epsisodes/mental-health-and-writing-roundtable&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of poetry, I&#39;m volunteering at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lyrafest.com/&quot;&gt;Lyra Festival&lt;/a&gt; in Bristol over the next couple of weeks. It looks to be a really fascinating series of events, I&#39;m also competing in the slam. If you&#39;d like to come along to the qualifying rounds you can sign up on zoom &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lyrafest.com/#events/e72148&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After swearing never to do it again, I&#39;ve given this site another spruce up. I replaced my creaking, stapled together code with theme called &lt;a href=&quot;https://mmistakes.github.io/minimal-mistakes/&quot;&gt;Minimal Mistakes&lt;/a&gt; and I&#39;m a lot happier with it. I&#39;ve also spruced up my &lt;a href=&quot;https://notes.davidralphlewis.co.uk/&quot;&gt;notes pages&lt;/a&gt; to make them more legible and removed all analytics. I don&#39;t have any comments on the pages either so now the only way to contact me is by email. A bit of a spring clean of my digital footprint. I&#39;m pleased with this latest evolution of the site, it&#39;s much more how I wanted it to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Reality Adjustments</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/reality-adjustments" />
    <updated>2022-03-18T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/reality-adjustments</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I&#39;m releasing an interactive poetry pamphlet called &lt;em&gt;Reality Adjustments.&lt;/em&gt; It&#39;s a surreal dive into a city that is always changing, with mutating streets, strange jobs and one or two apocalypses There are different paths to follow, multiple different endings and elements that change depending on where you have been before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started this project as a traditional poetry pamphlet, in a book format and worked on it for a couple of years. But I was never happy with the sequencing of the poems. The structure of the pamphlet seemed to change every time I looked at it. So after having it rejected a few times from publishers, I rewrote it using &lt;a href=&quot;https://twinery.org/&quot;&gt;TWINE&lt;/a&gt;, an open source interactive fiction tool. It was useful to animate and change the text, turning in from a linear experience to a more interactive one. It&#39;s been a lot of fun adapting the project into this new format, visually laying out paths and learning a new form of code. I also added in some erasures and some AI generated images from &lt;a href=&quot;https://pixray.gob.io/text2image/&quot;&gt;Pixray&lt;/a&gt; which seemed to fit the general unsettling tone. The result is somewhere between a work of interactive fiction and a poetry pamphlet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mostly I made it for my own amusement, but I also wanted to publish these fever dreams that have haunted me for the last couple of years. I&#39;m releasing it for free but if you like it you can always drop a few quid in my &lt;a href=&quot;https://ko-fi.com/davidralphlewis&quot;&gt;tip jar.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Huge thanks to Cat Balaq and Elizabeth McGeown for feedback on the poems when this project was still a traditional pamphlet as well as Melissa Wiseman for proof-reading and play testing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can play it below or go &lt;a href=&quot;https://davidralphlewis.itch.io/reality-adjustments&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt; It will work on mobile, but you probably need to be on a larger computer. I hope you enjoy it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://itch.io/embed/1444945?bg_color=e1d9c2&amp;amp;link_color=ed4b32&amp;amp;border_color=ed4b32&quot; width=&quot;552&quot; height=&quot;167&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://davidralphlewis.itch.io/reality-adjustments&quot;&gt;Reality Adjustments by David Ralph Lewis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Construction</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/construction" />
    <updated>2022-03-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/construction</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;div&gt;
You imagined | a field transmuted | into endless red bricks.&lt;br&gt;
You | hammered a sign | into the soil and | walked away.&lt;br&gt;
Now we carve | out mud and sand | mix and bake together&lt;br&gt;
earth | into our inferno | churn the loose |  ground into cubes&lt;br&gt;
make straight | lines out of leaves | that only want to curve.&lt;br&gt;
You | had a simple idea | thought a while | and called it a city.&lt;br&gt;
We are the ones | who stacked the | ground on top of itself,&lt;br&gt;
who | spun streets from | the threads of | the slip breeze.&lt;br&gt;
And when this | empty space has | been alchemically set &lt;br&gt;
into |  a new epicentre | of industry and | fearful commerce &lt;br&gt;
there will be no | monument to all | of our cracked hands &lt;br&gt;
that | struggled against | nature to lay out | these streets. &lt;br&gt;
Our fingerprints | will instead be | embedded into concrete &lt;br&gt;
the | echo of our voices | will be audible | in every room. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote the first draft of this at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/BristolTonic&quot;&gt;Bristol Tonic&lt;/a&gt;, in the half time. The prompt was &#39;We built this city&#39;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really like using prompts and timers to generate new work. The time constraint (ten minutes in this case) sharpens the mind and forces you to grab onto something from the prompt, even if it is an idea you would never write. This one in particular went in different directions than I expected. I must have been thinking of the Colston statue. It wasn&#39;t perfect after ten minutes, but I had the bones of a poem I could tweak and change. Thanks once again to Tonic for the chance to write something.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2022 February Input</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/2022-february-input" />
    <updated>2022-03-03T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/2022-february-input</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;February has flown by on gales and storms. I&#39;ve been really busy, performing two feature sets for Fen Speak and (Sm)art Festival, which were wonderful. I also applied and got a new job, turned 34 and spent too many hours lost in Hyrule. Phew. As a consequence of all this real life business, the things I have consumed have been limited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;52 Ways to Read a Poem&lt;/em&gt; by Ruth Padel- I read this as I wanted to improve my close reading of poetry. This book is incredibly useful for that, with 52 poems analysed in terms of the language and form. It tends towards the academic, and I wasn&#39;t always convinced by the readings but I found it clear and a useful resource to improve my own reading.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Films&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Moonfall&lt;/em&gt;- All you need to know about this film is one of the main characters receives a phone call early on where the caller id is simply &#39;NASA&#39;. A very, very stupid film. I quite enjoyed the experience of watching it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Little Joe&lt;/em&gt;- A sterile, strange twist on a body snatchers film. It will make you fearful of plants. The strange, dissonant music, the off centre shots and the deliberately false acting combine to create an unsettling atmosphere of barely contained threat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prospect&lt;/em&gt;- Very much the anti &lt;em&gt;Moonfall&lt;/em&gt;, this is a low budget science fiction film that has more world-building, style and ideas than films five times it&#39;s budget. It throws you in with no explanation and part of the delight is picking up on the details of this world and understanding it. It&#39;s tense and beautifully shot, with some amazing core performances. I absolutely loved it, seek it out if you can.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TV Shows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Book of Boba Fett&lt;/em&gt;- I&#39;ve never seen a series so disinterested in it&#39;s main character, to the point where he barely features in two episodes out of seven. There&#39;s some good ideas buried in here but it got lost under the weight of the wider Star Wars universe. It suffers from the Marvel problem of being a stepping stone onto other stories instead of focusing on a single story.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cobra Kai- Series 4&lt;/em&gt;- There&#39;s one episode of this series that is 80% montage and it is great. Cobra Kai somehow makes 80&#39;s cheese work again, whilst having believable characters and satisfying arcs. It&#39;s an entertaining watch that knows exactly the right tone to strike.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s it for now. Maybe I&#39;ll read more than one book this month, who knows?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Monochrome Memories</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/monochrome-memories" />
    <updated>2022-02-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/monochrome-memories</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2022/monochrome.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: Elsewhere, the ghost lingers/forever in black and white/ contorted beyond recognition./But over time it welcomes stillness&quot; title=&quot;February is the month most devoid of colour&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken from an old Mojo Magazine.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2022 January Input</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/2022-january-input" />
    <updated>2022-02-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/2022-january-input</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the early days of this blog (5 years and almost 400 posts ago) I used to do monthly roundups. I&#39;ve fallen out of the practice but have decided to revive it for this year, having been inspired by&lt;a href=&quot;https://kottke.org/22/01/my-recent-media-diet-end-2021.&quot;&gt;Jason Kottke&lt;/a&gt; and others. After all, what is a personal website for if not for my ill informed opinions on popular culture? So here is the media I have consumed for January 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;How to Do Nothing&lt;/em&gt; by Jenny Odell- I liked the theory and ideas behind this book more than the actual explanations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gideon the Ninth&lt;/em&gt; by Tamsyn Muir- A fun combination of high fantasy and science fiction, with some necromancy thrown in for good measure. The setting and characters felt unique and different, but the lore dragged it down.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Humour&lt;/em&gt; by Stanley Donward- Very short, strange short stories/ prose poems. I first read Stanley Donward when I was doing my playwriting masters twelve years ago. Reading him again, it&#39;s amazing how much I have been influenced by these singular stories and how much I have tried to emulate them in my own work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Equal Rites&lt;/em&gt; by Terry Pratchett- I&#39;m reading through the Discworld books again, very slowly. Now I&#39;m an adult I can see the social satire much more clearly. The first two books are funny but patchy. This is the first one in the series that feels like a complete story from beginning to end. It also introduces Granny Weatherwax, who appears in this book fully formed and a force of nature.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Bible II&lt;/em&gt; by Sam J. Grudgings- You should all go out and get this poetry book. It uses biblical metaphors to talk about addiction and recovery and is dense in the best way, every line sparks off new images in your head. It&#39;s painful in places but also beautiful. I read it slowly over a month and it is a book to savour. Sam has created a unique poetics that is uniquely his.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Drive Your Plow Over the Bones of the Dead&lt;/em&gt; by Olga Tokarczuk, translated by Antonia Lloyd-Jones: Beautifully written, weird combination of murder mystery and obscure mythology. I enjoyed it but found the main character irritating, which obscured the central message of the book. An odd read.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Films&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Remains of the Day&lt;/em&gt;- Just masterful. I loved the restraint of the performances, everything that remains unsaid and the overwhelming melancholy. It&#39;s a beautiful film and a fantastic adaptation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ready Player One&lt;/em&gt;- The best thing I can say about this film is it is just not very good, whereas the book is actively hateful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Matrix: Resurrections&lt;/em&gt;- Sure, it&#39;s a confusing mess, but its an entertaining confusing mess. I&#39;d much rather see film makers try something different and fail rather than watch the same story again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;TV&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Schitts Creek&lt;/em&gt;- A warm bath of a show that you sink into and enjoy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Marvelous Mrs. Maisel&lt;/em&gt; Season 1- Funny and well paced, it is a great exploration of why people want to perform. You like almost every character, even the ones who make mistakes. It&#39;s Amy Sherman-Palladino&#39;s best work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Other&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Apocrypals&lt;/em&gt; (podcast)- Two non believers read the bible and try not to be jerks. This is a fascinating and often silly dive into the Bible, with a biblical scholar on the show providing historical, cultural and linguistic context for each book. Their dive into the Gospels and Genesis are fascinating and has me reading the Bible along with them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s it for this month. I&#39;m going to try and keep my notes and &lt;a href=&quot;https://notes.davidralphlewis.co.uk/now&quot;&gt;what I&#39;m up to now&lt;/a&gt; more up to date.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Accumulated Weight</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/accumulated-weight" />
    <updated>2022-01-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/accumulated-weight</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2022/carrying.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: at the start of a new year/ you carry remnants/of endless mystery&quot; title=&quot;mysteries like why I continue to make these five years on&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken from Crack Magazine January 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Books of 2021</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/books-of-2021" />
    <updated>2022-01-06T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/books-of-2021</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last year I got through 65 books. (I&#39;ve kept a list &lt;a href=&quot;https://notes.davidralphlewis.co.uk/books-read-2021&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) Because I&#39;m not really using GoodReads anymore,  I thought I would curate a few of my highlights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;Solutions and Other Problems&lt;/em&gt; - Allie Brosh&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a long absence, Allie Brosh returns with a book that is equal parts hillarious and heartbreaking. It&#39;s a book about piecing yourself together again after tragedy, told through a combination of prose and simple cartoons that are incredibly expressive. I picked this up on a whim in a book shop and I&#39;m so glad I did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;No One Is Talking About This&lt;/em&gt; - Patricia Lockwood&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar to Allie Brosh, in this book Patricia Lockwood is laugh out loud funny in one section, then in the second half it becomes sadder and quieter. Written in a series of tweet style small paragraphs, this is a book that perfectly captures the whiplash and strangeness of being on social media. I&#39;ve never read a book that is so intently a product of the internet age that manages to critique it at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lanny&lt;/em&gt; - Max Porter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just your standard story of an ancient pagan spirit kidnapping a child, and the manhunt that ensues within the village. &lt;em&gt;Lanny&lt;/em&gt; weaves and jumps to different perspectives and voices, with experimental language and strange, off-beat poetic sections. For all the experimentation however, this manages to be an emotional rich story that examines outsiders and the violence underneath English society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Actual&lt;/em&gt; - Inua Ellams&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You would expect  series of poems, all starting with &amp;quot;fuck&amp;quot; to be furious. Of course, there is rage in these poems, especially in the multi-part &amp;quot;Fuck// Empire&amp;quot;, with its withering repetition and bluntly stated atrocities. But there&#39;s also joy and beauty. I love the sequencing of this collection, how one poem feeds into the next one. It&#39;s essential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;Low&lt;/em&gt;- Chrissy Williams&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another masterful exercise in sequencing, &lt;em&gt;Low&lt;/em&gt; ranges from darkly funny to full of tragedy. The variety of these poems and the unique approaches to form never diminish their power but instead show a master poet at work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rebecca&lt;/em&gt; - Daphne du Maurier&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How has it taken me this long to read &lt;em&gt;Rebecca?&lt;/em&gt; I&#39;ve long been aware of it as a classic but never actually got round to reading it. Well, more fool me. &lt;em&gt;Rebecca&lt;/em&gt; is strange and cruel, with sentences that unfold in your mind with the power of a dream. It&#39;s tightly paced and still shocking after all these years. It also finishes in the perfect place, not so much a cliff hanger but more leaving you right in a singular moment of horror.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;White Teeth&lt;/em&gt; - Zadie Smith&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another one for the &#39;should have read ages ago&#39; club. &lt;em&gt;White Teeth&lt;/em&gt; deals with colonialism, war and extremism, but with such a lightness of touch and a joy of writing that it is an utter delight. Zadie Smith winds multiples characters and histories together, making it look effortless. The narrator&#39;s voice throughout both mocks the characters and their blindspots whilst being affectionate towards them. It&#39;s fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;Circe&lt;/em&gt;- Madeline Miller&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similar to Pat Barker&#39;s &lt;em&gt;The Silence of the Girls&lt;/em&gt;, this explores foundational greek myths from a female perspective. Telling the story of the odyssey (and beyond) from the perspective of Circe trapped on her island, it is a lyrical, beautifully written novel. It exposes the violence and cruelty of the original mythology while still capturing the power of the stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wanderlust: A History of Walking&lt;/em&gt; - Rebecca Solnit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a vague resolution to read more non fiction last year. It didn&#39;t really work. As the world turned itself inside out again, I preferred the comfort of fiction and poetry. However, I did read this excellent book about an action many of take for granted. The history of walking is linked with class, with social change and with gender. Rebecca Solnit examines all this and more&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;Earthlings&lt;/em&gt;- Sayaka Murata&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This caught me completely by surprise. It&#39;s a book that goes in some very extreme directions that I was not expecting at all, especially given the initial careful banality of detail and social observation. This is a book that explores alienation and dehumanisation, that sneaks up on you with it&#39;s violence and intensity. To say any more would ruin the impact this novel can have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;What if Stars&lt;/em&gt;- Beth Hartley&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The opposite of &lt;em&gt;Earthlings&lt;/em&gt;, this is a book to restore your faith in humanity. Beth Hartley writes poems with care and humanity. Rooted in the fens, this collection is full of compassion and love, with beautiful, resonant poems throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fontanelle&lt;/em&gt;- Helen Shepherd&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s lovely when people you know release books. Helen is a stalwart of the Bristol poetry scene, having run an open mic night called Satellite of Love for years. Her debut collection is a deeply personal look at birth and life. Helen writes beautifully about her work as a midwife, family history and even poems about the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ll leave the reflecting there for now. I was going to write another blog post about films but it would just be me banging on about &lt;em&gt;The Green Knight&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/uncertain-art/&quot;&gt;again.&lt;/a&gt; This year I am going to try and write little summaries like this more regularly, so I don&#39;t leave it as a reflection exercise in January.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>2021 in Review: Who knows anything anymore?</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/2021-in-review-who-knows-anything-anymore" />
    <updated>2021-12-31T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/2021-in-review-who-knows-anything-anymore</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yet again, I sit down to summarize the year gone by and yet again I find myself struggling for words. It has been another year of chaos and contradiction, of pandemic and freedom, of confusion and connection. As I write, I am ill with COVID 19, somewhat inevitably being hit by omicron. Of course, I am lucky enough to be vaccinated, so I have avoided the worst of it. I started the year in lockdown and end it in isolation. Inbetween have been moments of connection and moments of joy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking back over my previous posts (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2016-the-year-the-internet-took-over/&quot;&gt;2016&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2017-review-laughing-naked-emperor/&quot;&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2018-in-review-a-poem/&quot;&gt;2018&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2019-year-of-contradictions/&quot;&gt;2019.&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/2019-year-of-contradictions/&quot;&gt;2020&lt;/a&gt;) what strikes me is a sense of accelerating chaos. In most of them I say the year was the worst one yet and hope for better. This year feels different. It&#39;s not that the chaos and insanity has lessened, its more the fact I am resigned to it. Everyone I speak to is similar. We are all exhausted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s no wonder this year has been defined by fatigue. In the UK, we started the year in a lockdown that was the most brutal yet as cases soared and the death rate exploded. I spent a lot of the first half of the year furious. I was angry at the incompetence of our government, who combined corruption and greed with a callous disregard for the lives of the population. I was angry at the virus that has upended all of our lives. I was  angry at my inability to do anything meaningful or focus on anything for long. But anger burns itself out fast, leaving behind exhaustion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then in the later half of the year, a release. We started seeing other people again. Cases were still high, but hospitalization was low. We had the miracle of the vaccines. I saw people in real life and each time it felt glorious. I went to weddings, saw friends and talked nonsense, listened to poets pour their hearts out in small rooms. It felt like a real return to some sort of normality. I also never took it for granted. How precious the presence of others is. How beautiful it is to be in the company of people you love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, of course, it all went wrong again. One of the commonalities of the last few years has been the rate of change- too fast for most people to keep track of. Omicron emerged and within a couple of weeks, new records were being broken. We&#39;ve all been here before and a collective response was &amp;quot;Oh no, not again.&amp;quot; It&#39;s a lot to deal with emotionally, even leaving aside the rising tide of authoritarian measures our government is taking. Banning legitimate protest, scrapping human rights and demonising refugees would set massive alarm bells ringing in the best of times, yet this year they barely registered over the noise of everything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this, the relentless nature of the pandemic and the constant change is exhausting. It&#39;s a lot. So no wonder we all find ourselves fatigued. We are living through massive trauma that is going to have huge impacts for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, personally, it has been a pretty good year. I got engaged to my wonderful partner of seven years, passed my driving test and got a promotion at work. I had my writing and art featured in some dream places, and I&#39;ve enjoyed some fantastic collaborations. For all of this and more, I am extremely grateful. I&#39;m lucky in so many countless ways. It just goes to show that not all change is bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So where do we go from here? I don&#39;t know. I still hold hope for a better world, but I know we may have to go through more changes and more unexpected developments to get there. One thing I hope is that sense of being together is never taken for granted. Given the loss and the pain we have all experienced, I hope we can open our minds and become more empathetic to the suffering of others and rebuild our society to one based on kindness and compassion. That is the only way forward I can see, not one built on fear and suspicion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of 2019, I was a sweet summer child who had no idea of what the next two years would involve. I wrote this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contradictions will only get worse because we’re living in crisis... We find it hard to recognise a crisis when its far off but now, in the middle of it, we can react and join together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, two years later we find the contradictions hard to bear and the crisis still ranging. We have united together in so many different ways. I just hope we can keep the momentum going and demand a better and fairer world, one not ruled by the greedy, the rich and the self-interested but one that works for the most amount of people.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lost to Fog</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/lost-to-fog" />
    <updated>2021-12-08T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/lost-to-fog</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2021/fog.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: from the north/ an otherworldly haze./These days, out of focus/ expand in unpredictable directions/ and there are moments/lost to discord&quot; title=&quot;Clearly I am full of festive joy&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken from Crack Magazine November 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Communion</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/communion" />
    <updated>2021-11-15T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/communion</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/assets/images/articles/2021/communion.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;erasure poem: In liminal spaces/ I speak to the unimaginable./ Words falter,/ I return to silence&quot; title=&quot;I love articles printed on black backgrounds&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taken from Crack Magazine November 2021.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you like this, I have three erasures in the upcoming issue of &lt;em&gt;Neon&lt;/em&gt; Magazine. Massive thanks to them. You can pre-order the issue &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.neonbooks.org.uk/product-tag/issue-53/&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also have a small shivery poem alongside some brilliant poets in the &lt;em&gt;Black Bough Poetry&lt;/em&gt; anthology &lt;em&gt;Christmas &amp;amp; Winter - Volume 2&lt;/em&gt;. Again, huge thanks to the editor for taking the poem in. You can find that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.blackboughpoetry.com/about-3&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Uncertain Art</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/uncertain-art" />
    <updated>2021-11-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/uncertain-art</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been thinking about &lt;em&gt;The Green Knight&lt;/em&gt; ever since I saw it a month ago. The film is a hypnotic blend of English myth, dream like strangeness and stiking imagery.[^1] . What has kept me returning to the film in my head is how little it explains for the audience. There is a clear quest with monsters and talking animals, but within this framework it resists easy interpretation. There&#39;s no simple explanation of what the different perspectives mean or why Gaiwan is on the quest. Instead, it leaves the meaning up to the audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m increasingly drawn to art like this, that is allows space for nuance and interpretation. Perhaps because mainstream films like Marvel offer clear character motivations, as well as obvious bad guys to defeat. It&#39;s refreshing to see something that diverges from this formula. Perhaps I am also tired of the three act structure and the heroes quest that has become so formulaic. Or maybe it&#39;s because social media tends towards strident declarations of facts in the face of increasing chaos. Regardless of the actual reasons, I find art that I have to sit with and figure out myself more interesting at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where the meaning is uncertain, it&#39;s easy to say its dismiss these films as random or uncrafted.[^2] I&#39;d argue instead that when it is done well, the meaning is uncertain but the internal imagery and design is consistent and tight. There is just none of the easy answers usually available to us. The artist may have a meaning in mind, but it is not revealed to the audience, creating a space where the audience can add their own meaning. J David Osborne explores this in his guest podcast for &lt;a href=&quot;https://permanentlymoved.libsyn.com/&quot;&gt;301 Permamently Moved&lt;/a&gt;, saying:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mode of not-knowing, however, drops a reader or a viewer or a gamer into a world that is tightly controlled, internally consistent, yet completely unavailable. Not cold, per se, but closed off.
...
for some people, the best thing art can do is open up that space in your mind that lets you fill in the blanks, a place that was there in childhood before you became weighed down with the burden of knowing things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://brokenriverbooks.com/2021/06/12/301-transcript-06-12-21/&quot;&gt;The Dark Souls Method&lt;/a&gt;- J David Osborne&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is increasingly what I seek from the art I engage with, a space where I can fill in my own interpretations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we tend to accept this more readily in music than in other art forms. Look at the song &lt;em&gt;Spanish Translation&lt;/em&gt; by Low:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=x0TJrlemmVQ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s one of my favourite songs from the last few years and hits me every time. But I could not tell you what it means. Why does the Spanish translation change the perspective of the singer so much? We never know. But we are used to feeling the emotion of music more. The power of the instrumentation, that crash of noise in the chorus and the beautiful vocals in the background all add to the experience of the song. It&#39;s fitting, because it is also a song about uncertainty. Like &lt;em&gt;The Green Knight&lt;/em&gt;, it provokes an emotional response but what it means is unclear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhat inevitably, this leads us onto poetry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In school, we are often taught that there is one meaning of a poem that the author intended. We excavate this meaning like an autopsy, peeling apart the layers of language to see how it works. This is fine for an understanding of how the form works, but it misses the fact that this dense art form full of imagery and metaphor can often be used to explore not knowing. Look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://pen.org/stars-are-shredding-machines%C2%9D-and-from-my-mothers-sleep/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stars are Shredding Machines&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Christain Hawkey. My interpretation of this poem has changed multiple times since I first read it and I&#39;m not sure any of these are &#39;right&#39;. Poetry is used instead to explore the space of not knowing. We can simply experience the poem instead of interpreting it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all these examples, what I enjoy is becoming an active participant in the work. Instead of didactically laying down the interpretation of a piece of art, these works allow for multiple meanings to exist at once. The artist may have a meaning in mind when they created it, but the audience becomes an equal participant in crating the meaning, which may be different to the intention. It&#39;s freeing to make your own mind up, but also to sit in the uncertainty for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[^1]: It&#39;s brilliant. Go see it if you get the chance.
[^2]: David Lynch films often have this accusation thrown at them, perhaps because they are so dream-like in feel.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Skeleton Trees</title>
    <link href="https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/skeleton-trees" />
    <updated>2021-01-13T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://www.davidralphlewis.co.uk/blog/skeleton-trees</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/articles/2021/skeletontree1.jpg&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/articles/2021/skeletontree2.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/articles/2021/skeletontree3.jpeg&quot; class=&quot;responsive&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Winter erases the land with a shaky hand. For a few months, we roam in the smudges, wondering where the detail went.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>